<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="116"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[ISSN: 2583-7044 (Online)
                                                     Title: Veritas.

                                                 Title: Veritas.]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[MESSAGE  FROM  THE  PRINCIPAL
    MESSAGE                            FROM                   THE               PRINCIPAL


                                    Rev. Fr. Augustine George































      Forensic science plays a pivotal role                  in Biotechnology and Forensic Science and
      in the criminal justice system of any                  Master’s  in  Science  in  Forensic  Science
      country. As it deals with the scientif-                programmes. The department ensures to
      ic examination of evidence, it makes                   conduct sessions for students from ex-
      it more valuable in assisting the court                perts in the field at an international level.
      to make the correct judgement. Initi-
      ating from the scene of crime, forensic                The Forensic Science newsletter, ‘Veritas’
      science is a discipline which should be                is a bi-annual newsletter published by

      highlighted efficiently throughout the                 the department of forensic science which
      process of criminal justice.                           compiles articles written by the forensic
                                                             science students on matters relating to
      Forensic science has evolved along                     research areas, case studies, newer tech-
      with science in the implementation                     nologies etc. I am happy to state that the
      of technology to aid in the process of                 department has procured an ISSN num-
      investigation of crime and analysis of                 ber for the newsletter, therefore making

      evidence. Fields like digital forensics                the newsletter and the articles in it more
      have paved the way for investigation                   valuable. This edition of Veritas will en-
      of new age crimes.                                     sure to bring to the readers more scien-
                                                             tific information and articles. The facul-
      The Department of Forensic Science at                  ty and students of the department have
      Kristu Jayanti College (Autonomous),                   worked tremendously to ensure this edi-
      Bengaluru, has progressed very well                    tion comes out well to its readers.
      and in the fifth year of their existence
      have achieved a lot. The department                    On this occasion, I congratulate the de-

      runs a Bachelor’s (single major), Bach-                partment of Forensic Science and the ed-
      elor’s (Double major)                                  itorial board of Veritas for the successful
                                                             and  effective  issue  of  the  third  issue  of
                                                             the first volume.



    Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[THE
                                                                                                 AN
                                                                                       DE
              MESSAGE FROM THE DEAN
              MESSAGE FROM
                                         Dr. Calistus Jude A.L.































        It is a delight that the Department of               This  edition has in store insightful arti-
        Forensic Science, Kristu Jayanti Col-                cles, research updates and reports of the

        lege has come out with its fifth edi-                myriad programmes organised by the de-
        tion of newsletter “Veritas”. This edi-              partment.    The  flipbook  version  makes

        tion is a testament to the dedication                the newsletter more interactive.   I con-
        and passion of the students, alumni                  gratulate the department for procuring
                                                             an ISSN number for Veritas which makes
        and faculty members of the depart-                   this publication more valuable.
        ment.

                                                             I would like to extend my heartfelt grat-
        The academic community of the De-                    itude to the editorial team, student and

        partment consider Veritas as a plat-                 faculty contributors and the creative team
        form to showcase the achievements,                   who have worked tirelessly to bring this

        research and contributions of the                    newsletter to fruition. Their efforts have
        department, its students and faculty                 truly captured the spirit and vibrancy of

        members.  It  reflects  the  impressive              the department.
        growth of the department and high-                   I look forward to the continued growth

        lights the role played by the students               and  success  of  the  department  and  the
        and faculty in creating awareness on                 contributions we will make to the field of

        the latest trends in forensic science.               forensic science in the years to come.















                                                                                      Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[ADVISORY BOARD






          - Fr. Dr. Augustine George, Principal

          - Fr. Lijo P Thomas, Vice Principal & Chief Finance Officer
          - Fr. Emmanuel P. J., Director, Kristu Jayanti College of Law,Director, Office

          of International and Domestic Relations, Jayantian Extension Services &
          Jayantian Alumni Association, Faculty, Department of Psychology

          - Fr. Jais V Thomas, Financial Administrator, Faculty Member, Commerce and
          Management

          - Fr. Som Zacharia, Director , Infrastructure Planning and Development
          - Fr. Joshy Mathew, Director, Library and Information Centre, Director, HR

          Department, Head, Department of English
          - Fr.  Deepu  Joy,  Director,  Student  Welfare  Office,  Faculty  Member,

          Department of Life Sciences




                               EDITORIAL BOARD


                                              FACULTY








          - Prof. Don Caeiro, Coordinator, Department of Forensic Science
          - Prof. Suchita Rawat, Assistant professor, Department of Forensic Science

          - Prof. Devi. S, Assistant professor, Department of Forensic Science
          - Prof. Aashika N, Assistant professor, Department of Forensic Science

          - Prof. Shristi Aich, Assistant professor, Department of Forensic Science
          - Prof. Mayank David Raiborde, Assistant professor, Department of Forensic

          Science
          - Prof. Aditi, Assistant professor, Department of Forensic Science

          - Prof. Himani Sharma Assistant professor, Department of Forensic Science
          - Prof. Neha Vishe, Assistant professor, Department of Forensic Science

          - Prof.  Annapoorni  Ammal,  Assistant  professor,  Department  of  Forensic
          Science

          - Prof. Vismaya S R, Teaching Assistant, Department of Forensic Science
          - Prof. Anna Maria Jose, Teaching Assistant, Department of Forensic Science

          - Prof. Retty Mary Shaji, Teaching Assistant, Department of Forensic Science]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[EDITORIAL BOARD STUDENTS



                                              REVIEW TEAM























                Simeon Hanesh Das               Anumita Mazumdar                 Jency Mathew Sunil
                III Sem B.Sc (Hons) FS           V Sem B.Sc (Hons) FS             III Sem B.Sc (Hons) FS

                                            EDITITNG TEAM

























                       Sneha M                  Bhavya Kamath                  Allen Jose Tomyachen
                 III Sem B.Sc (Hons) FS        V Sem B.Sc (Hons) FS              III Sem B.Sc (Hons) FS

                                        DESIGNING TEAM

























         Varun Sai S            Merien Abraham            A. Sherlin Gomez         Pereppaden Ancila Robinson
    III Sem B.Sc (Hons) FS     V Sem B.Sc (Hons) FS       V Sem B.Sc (Hons) FS           III Sem B.Sc (Hons) FS]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[SILVER JUBILEE OF KRISTU

         JAYANTI COLLEGE AUTONOMOUS



































                Amidst the bustling streets of Bengaluru, India, an educational

                institution has stood the test of time and left a lasting mark on
                the world of higher education. With a history of 25 years, Kris-
                tu Jayanti College is more than just an academic institution.

                It is a testament to the founding visionaries and the countless
                others who contributed to its growth.


                Kristu Jayanti College was established in 1999 and is managed
                by the Bodhi Niketan Trust. It was founded by the members of

                the Carmelite Province of St. Joseph of Mary Immaculate (CMI),
                which  is  India’s  first  indigenous  religious  congregation.  This
                community is the epitome of the dreams and visions of the 19th

                century Indian educator and social reformer St. Kuriakose Cha-
                vara. The university started with 1 course, 9 students and 3 fac-
                ulty members and has now grown rapidly to 10,000 students,
                33 UG programmes, 17 PG programmes, and 3 PG diploma pro-
                grammes. Over the years, Kristu Jayanti College has embarked

                on a journey of academic expansion.]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[New courses and programmes are being introduced to meet
                  the changing needs of a globalised world.



                  The institute’s commitment to educational excellence has
                  paid  off,  achieving  consistently  high  rankings  and  accredi-
                  tation from prestigious educational organisations. Carefully

                  selected for their expertise and passion for teaching, our fac-
                  ulty has played an important role in shaping our academ-
                  ic community. The institute’s commitment to research and
                  innovation is evident in the numerous publications, patents,
                  and projects undertaken by both faculty and students.  The

                  physical  infrastructure  of Kristu  Jayanti  College has devel-
                  oped in parallel with its academic activities. State-of-the-art
                  classrooms, well-equipped laboratories, and modern recre-

                  ational facilities have transformed the campus into a vibrant
                  centre of learning and collaboration. In addition, the insti-
                  tute’s  eco-friendly initiatives and green spaces on campus
                  reflects its commitment to environmental sustainability.



                  The college is affiliated with Bengaluru North University and
                  was reaccredited with the ‘A++’ grade by NAAC in 2021. It
                  has been an independent institution since 2013. “Light and

                  Prosperity” is the institution’s vision; its mission is to pro-
                  vide educational opportunities to all ambitious young people,
                  enabling them to excel in all aspects of life.]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[Kristu Jayanti College, celebrating its 25th anniversary,
                  stands as a beacon of educational excellence and a testament

                  to the transformative power of education. The college’s rich
                  history is more than just a chronicle, it is a story of resil-
                  ience, growth, and an unwavering commitment to shaping

                  the minds and characters of the next generation. Ever-evolv-
                  ing, Kristu Jayanti College continues to be a dynamic force in
                  the world]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[CONTENTS















                                                                       CTIVITIES
                                                          ENT A
                                      DEP
                                              AR
                                                    TM
                     1                DEPARTMENT ACTIVITIES
                                      Actvities Conductes By The Department Of
                                      Forensic Science
                                      RESEARCH ARTICLES
                     2                RESEAR           CH AR        TICLES

                                      Student - Performed Researches Studying
                                      Topics Under The Branch Of Forensic Science


                                      GLOBAL NEWS UPDATES RELATED
                      3               GLOBAL NEWS UPDATES RELATED
                                      TO FORENSIC SCIENCE
                                      TO FORENSIC SCIENCE
                                      Latest Technologies Discovered In The Field


                                      CASE STUDIES
                      4               CASE S        TUDIES
                                      Detailed Writeups Of Cases That Have Occured
                                      In The Recent Past



                      5               FEA     TURE AR            TICLES
                                      FEATURE ARTICLES
                                      A Breakdown Of Various Concepts Concerning
                                      The Field Of Forensic Science



                                                     TURE REVIEW
                                                                                   S
                                      LITERA
                      6               LITERATURE REVIEWS
                                      A Critical Analysis And Report Of Educational
                                      Subject Matters]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[DEPARTMENT ACTIVITIES











                               International Conference On Advances
                  1            Int  er  nat   iona    l Conf     er  ence On Adv            ances
                               In F
                               In Forensic Science [ICAFS] 2023
                                      or
                                          ensic Science [ICAFS] 2023
                                   QUISITOR
                               IN
                   2           INQUISITOR                 e F   or  ensic Science F             est
                               Int
                               Inter-Collegiate Forensic Science Fest
                                    er-
                                          Collegiat

                   3           KR   YPTOS – F          or  ensic Science Exhibit                  ion
                               KRYPTOS – Forensic Science Exhibition




                                                                                ensic P
                                                                    e - F
                                                                                                   hological
                              Exper
                                                                            or
                                                                                                 c
                                                              t
                                                                ur
                                         t Guest Lec
                                                                                             sy
                   4          Expert Guest Lecture - Forensic Psychological
                                                                ensic In
                                                            or
                                     hniques In F
                                 ec
                                                                                est
                                                                              v
                                                                                             ions
                                                                                      igat
                              T
                              Techniques In Forensic Investigations
                              Expert Guest Lecture - Forensic Aspects In
                                                                                ensic Aspec
                   5          Exper      t Guest Lec          t ur  e - F   or  ion                   ts In
                              Disaster Vic
                              Disaster Victim Identification
                                                     tim Identificat
                                                              t
                                                                ur
                              Exper
                                                                    e - Biological Samples
                                         t Guest Lec
                   6          Expert Guest Lecture - Biological Samples
                                                                y
                                                                  sis
                              And Forensic Analysis
                                         or
                              And F
                                             ensic Anal
                              Ca   r eer Or      ient   at  ion Session : Cyber                sec   ur  it y
                              Career Orientation Session : Cybersecurity
                   7          And Digita          l F  or  ensics
                              And Digital Forensics
                   8          IN   DUS     TRIAL VISIT - CDFD                   , H  y  der   aba   d
                              INDUSTRIAL VISIT - CDFD, Hyderabad
                   9           INDUSTRIAL VISIT - RFSL, Mysore
                                                                                        sor
                                                                                              e
                                           TRIAL VISIT - RFSL, M
                                   DUS
                               IN
                                                                                      y
                 10           N  A  TION      AL SCIEN         CE D     A  Y
                              NATIONAL SCIENCE DAY
                                                            1


      Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE



             ON ADVANCES IN FORENSIC



                        SCIENCE [ICAFS] 2023






         Date: 20/04/2023 & 21/04/2023
         Details of participants: External delegates 109; Internal delegates 336.


         Resource Persons:

         1.  Dr. V V Pillay, eminent forensic toxicologist, Amrita Institute of Medical Sciences
            and Research Centre, Kochi,
         2.  Shri. Keshav Kumar, IPS (retd.), Former ADGP, Gujarat state police,
         3.  Dr.  William  Goodwin, Reader in Forensic Genetics, University of Central  Lan-

            cashire, UK,
         4.  Dr. Carlos A Guitierrez, Secretary of Consensus body of ASB CSI from AAFS Stan-
            dards Board (ASB), USA,
         5.  Dr. S Venkata Raghava, Professor And  Head, Department Of Forensic Medicine

            And Toxicology , Bangalore Medical College And Research Institute and
         6.  Dr G B Aravind, Associate Professor and Coordinator of Forensic Science, Depart-
            ment of Forensic Medicine and Toxicology, JSS Medical College, Mysuru



         Brief Summary of Expert Guest lecture


         The department of Forensic Science at Kristu Jayanti College (Autonomous), Ben-
         galuru organised the 2nd International Conference on Advances in Forensic Science

         (ICAFS), 2023 on 20th and 21st April 2023 at the college campus. The conference was
         organised in a hybrid manner with delegates joining in person and over online video
         conferencing platforms.
         The conference witnessed 6 plenary sessions addressed by eminent forensic science re-

         searchers and professionals and 76 research paper and poster presentations both offline
         and onlineg.The plenary speakers uncluded Dr. V V Pillay, eminet forensic toxicologist
         Amrita Institute of Medical Sciences and Research Centre, Kochi, Shri. Keshav Kumar,
         IPS (retd.), Former ADGP, Gujarat state police, Dr. William Goodwin, Reader in Foren-

         sic Genetics, University of Central Lancashire, UK, Dr. Carlos A Guitierrez, Secretary
         of Consensus body of ASB CSI from AAFS Standards Board (ASB), USA, Dr. S Ven-
         kata Raghava, Professor And  Head, Department Of Forensic Medicine And Toxicolo-
         gy , Bangalore Medical College And Research Institute and Dr G B Aravind, Associate

         Professor and Coordinator of Forensic Science, Department of Forensic Medicine and
         Toxicology, JSS Medical College, Mysuru. The plenary sessions covered topics rang-
         ing from quality assurance to advanced forensic techniques of the future.




                                                            2                     Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[The conference was attended by more than 150 delegates from across India. It also
         witnessed 76 presentations by researchers and academicians of research in the various
         disciplines of forensic science. The paper and poster presentations were assessed by

         scientific panels and best papers and posters were awarded.
         The conference was inaugurated on 20th April by Shri. Keshav Kumar, IPS (retd.), For-
         mer ADGP, Gujarat state Police who listed the challenges facing the forensic science
         fraternity and outlined the government’s focus on improvement and modernisation of

         forensic services in the country. Fr. Jais V Thomas, Financial Administrator, Kristu
         Jayanti college presided the inauguration and exhorted the delegates to make good use
         of the 2 days and aspire for greater heights in the field of forensic science. Mr. Don
         Caeiro, Coordinator, Department of Forensic Science listed the progress made by the

         department and outlined the need for delegates to deliberate and discuss the techniques
         and tools available to utilize them in their full potential.
         The conference generated a lot of interest all around India and had delegates from
         neighbouring states and many faraway states of India.



         Photographs:


























































          Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1                        3]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[4                   Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[INTER-COLLEGIATE FORENSIC



             SCIENCE FEST ‘INQUISITOR’





         Title:  Inter-collegiate Forensic Fest- INQUISITOR 2023

         Date:  10/03/2023
         Number of participants:  17



         Objective:
         To stimulate and promote students to improve their understanding in their core skills
         and channel their participation to extra-curricular and co-curricular events.


         Brief write-up:



         The Forensic Science club, Unit of Forensic Science organised Inquisitor 2023, in-
         ter-collegiate forensic fest for students of forensic science in other colleges based in

         India. This forensic fest aimed at discovering students’ knowledge and understanding
         of the subject as it offered a wide science related events.
         The event was organised by the student coordinators of the Forensic Science club at
         Kristu Jayanti College, Bangalore. The BSc Forensic Science students at Kristu Jayanti
         College formed the working group and were event and team organisers. The partici-

         pants included the Forensic Science students from 4 different institutes across India.
         The fest was executed with a total of 7 events and was organised at its best of quality.
         The fest was conducted offline in the college campus. The high- spirited forensic fest

         started with preliminary rounds of various events on 10th March, 2023.
         The participants were given participant codes to ensure fairness and none of the internal
         students participated and the event was open only for external participants.
         7 events were organised which included - Crimetoonist (Sketching), i-witness (Obser-
         vation test), X-Word (Crossword), Cross examination (Case study presentation),  Wiz

         Quiz (Forensic Quiz), Room of Opinions (Debate), and Sherlock Holmes (Personality
         contest).
         The inaugural ceremony of the fest was presided over by Fr. Augustine George, Prin-

         cipal, Kristu Jayanti College, Bangalore and the guest of honour was Mr. Premjith,
         Director, Infosec-Texial Cyber Security, Bangalore. In his presidential address, Father
         enlightened about the importance of forensic science and its scope in everyday life. Mr.
         Premjith spoke about the existing avenues in Forensic Science and the future scopes.
         He encouraged students to take up newer domains and fields which are coming up in

         the field. He exhorted the faculty members to take up newer topics and help the students
         evolve into newer and brighter minds.
         In the valedictory ceremony, Fr. Jais V Mathew, Financial Administrator and






       Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1                          5]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[Dr Calistus Jude, Dean, Faculty of Science, Kristu Jayanti College felicitated the win-
         ners of various events and appreciated the Forensic Science club coordinators for hav-
         ing cducted the forensic fest successfully.



         List of Winners


          SNo     Prize                 Organisation

          1.      Overall Winners National Forensic Sciences University, Goa
          2.      Runners up            Jain University School of Sciences, JC Road, Bengaluru













































































                                                            6                     Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[KRYPTOS –



     FORENSIC SCIENCE EXHIBITION
     FORENSIC SCIENCE EXHIBITION


        Date: 27 February 2023



        Details of participants:
        Students from different Higher secondary (PU) schools and colleges teaching forensic

        science and allied programmes (120)
        Students of the department of forensic science (360)


        Venue: M1 Audi, Main Block



        Resource Persons:
        Dr. Hemalata M, Principal, Dr. MR Ambedkar Dental College, Bangalore
        Brief Summary of Expert Guest lecture

        Kryptos the forensic science exhibition was organised by the department of forensic sci-
        ence, Kristu Jayanti College on 27th February 2023. Being the first time, the exhibition
        garnered a lot of interest among students of the department and among nearby institu-
        tions.
        Dr. Hemalata M, Principal, Dr. MR Ambedkar Dental College, Bangalore inaugurated

        the event along with Fr. Dr. Augustine George, Principal, Kristu Jayanti college. During
        the inauguration the presidential address was delivered by Fr. Augustine George who
        stressed on the need for such events to improve the skill sets of students and he applaud-

        ed the students and teachers of the department for the effort in organising the exhibition.
        The inaugural address was delivered by Dr. Hemalata M, Principal, Dr. MR Ambedkar
        Dental College, Bangalore who explained the need for exhibitions and how these events
        help in developing the psycho-motor skills and the experiential skills among students.
        She also exhorted the students to never stop learning and to keep the mindset of chal-

        lenging defiance in times of uncertainty.
        A total of 15 chart posters, 23 digitally created infographic posters, 40 static models, 10
        dynamic models were created by the students, and teachers of the department. A total

        of 15 institutions visited the exhibition during the day and gave very positive feedback.
























       Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1                          7]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[FORENSIC PSYCHOLOGICAL



                                 TECHNIQUES IN



               FORENSIC INVESTIGATION






         Date: 17 February 2023
         Details of participants: B.Sc. Forensic Science students IV semester (122 students)


         Resource Persons: Dr. Priyanka Kacker, School of Forensic Psychology, National Fo-

         rensic Sciences University, Gandhinagar


         Brief Summary of Expert Guest lecture:



         The expert talk on Forensic Psychological techniques in Forensic Investigation was
         held on 17th February 2023 with the resource person Dr. Priyanka Kacker, School of
         Forensic Psychology, National Forensic Sciences University, Gandhinagar. The session
         was aimed at orienting the students of IVth semester BSc Forensic Science to the dif-

         ferent Forensic Psychology techniques used in forensic investigation.
         Techniques like polygraph, narco-analysis and brain fingerprinting were discussed in
         detail by the resource person. The different strengths and weaknesses of each technique
         was explained with different case studies to help students understand the application of

         these techniques.
         Legal admissibility of each technique was the next part of the lecture and the resource
         person took the students through the different landmark cases which led to use of these
         techniques in India and alongside the different recent legal admissibility issues these

         techniques were held into were explained in great detail.
         Students could also ask questions to the expert person and discuss some of their queries.
         The session was interactive and much useful in strengthening the knowledge learnt by
         students through the curriculum during this semester.





























                                                            8                   Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[FORENSIC ASPECTS IN DISASTER
     FORENSIC                            ASPECTS IN DISASTER


                  VICTIM IDENTIFICA
                  VICTIM IDENTIFICATION
                                                                                      TION



        Date: 09/03/2023
        Details of participants: B.Sc. VI Semester Forensic Science students.


        Resource Persons: Ms. Hansi Bansal, Assistant Professor, Government Institute of Fo-
        rensic Science, Nagpur



        Brief Summary of Expert Guest lecture


         The department of forensic science, Kristu Jayanti College, Bangalore organised an
        expert lecture titled ‘Forensic aspects in Disaster victim Identification’ on 09/03/2023.

        The resource person for this session was Ms. Hansi Bansal, Assistant Professor, Gov-
        ernment Institute of Forensic Science, Nagpur. The session was conducted online over
        the ZOOM platform.
        The session highlighted the different tools and techniques available for disaster victim

        identification. The students of 6th semester BSc Forensic Science have a course titled
        ‘DNA Typing’ where disaster victim identification forms a major portion of their train-
        ing.
        The resource person started the lecture by explaining the need and significance of disas-

        ter victim identification. The Red Cross guidelines and the formation of a new division
        in forensic science called ‘humanitarian forensics’ was underlined.
        The tools which were used traditionally and the newer more robust and skilled tech-
        niques were outlined and discussed in detail by the resource person. Tools like anthro-

        pology, DNA, heredity testing etc. were explained in great detail.
        The resource person also outlined the case studies where these tools and techniques have
        been used in the recent past both in India and abroad.
































       Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1                           9]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[10                   Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[BIOLOGICAL SAMPLES



                AND FORENSIC ANALYSIS






        Date: 9 March 2023
        Details of participants: IV semester B.Sc. Forensic Science. (121)



        Resource Persons:
        Dr. Ajay Rana, Scientist B, CFSL Hyderabad



        Brief Summary of Expert Guest lecture


        9th March 2023
        The Department of Forensic Science, Kristu Jayanti College, Autonomous organised

        the third expert lecture for the academic year Jan-June 2023 on the theme “Biological
        sample and forensic analysis” on March 9th, 2023. The session was held online via
        the ZOOM platform. Dr. Ajay Kumar Rana, Scientist B, CFSL, Hyderabad, was the
        resource person. The session started with a brief introduction of the speaker to the au-

        dience. Soon later, the session was taken over by the resource person. Sir introduced
        Forensic Science and the first case of Julius Cesar in forensic evidence. Sri explained
        that biological samples commonly detected blood, sperm, saliva, bone, flesh, bone, and
        saliva. Sir explained the notion of presumptive, confirmatory blood and species tests. .

        Sir also noted that FSL and CFSL removed blood grouping due to low discriminatory
        power. The secretors and non-secretors tests, as well as the saliva examination utilising
        the Phadebas test, were explained. Hair’s position as an exhibit has been expanded.
        Microscopic study of spermatozoa, P30 immunoassays, and SERATEC for vaginal cell

        secretion have all been explained. Sir mentioned the reference samples acquired from
        the accused or victim as blood or cheek swab, as well as biological samples collected
        for DNA profiling on mobile phones, glass bottles, bite marks, toothbrushes, and so on.
        The DNA profiling procedures, types of DNA polymorphisms such as autosomal STR,

        Y STR, X- STR, DNA extraction methods, DNA quantification in kits quantifier HP and
        DNA Trio kit, DNA amplification by thermal cycler, and


        DNA amplification by thermal cycler are all explained in depth. Finally, the floor was

        offered for questions, and each question was enthusiastically accepted and appropriately
        answered.















       Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1
                                                           11]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[12                  Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[CYBER SECURITY AND



                         DIGITAL FORENSICS





        Date: 17 April 2023
        Details of participants: VI semester B.Sc. Forensic Science.



        Resource Persons:  Ms. Brunda Anil Sastry, PG diploma student, Lambton College,
        Canada



        Brief Summary of Career orientation session


        17th April 2023
        The Department of Forensic Science, Kristu Jayanti College, Autonomous hosted the

        third career orientation lecture for the academic year Jan-June 2023 on the topic “Cyber-
        security and digital forensics” on April 17th, 2023. The session was held offline in the
        A1 Auditorium, Admin Block. Ms.Brunda, a PG diploma student at Lambton College in
        Mississauga, Canada, was the resource person. The event began with a brief introduc-

        tion of the speaker to the audience. The resource person swiftly took over the session.
        Madam clarified the fundamental distinction between digital forensic science and cyber-
        security. She went on to explain the various certifications available and touched on the
        employment roles of a digital forensic specialist. She then narrowed her discussion to

        cyber forensics fields such as red team and blue team. • She also informed the students
        about blue team certifications such as CompTIA Security+, Certified Information Sys-
        tems Security Professional (CISSP), Global Information Assurance Certification (GIAC
        Certification/GSEC), as well as red team certifications such as Certified Ethical Hacker

        (CEH)- EC Council, Cisco Certified Network Associate (CCNA) Security, and Certified
        Red Team Operations Professional (CRTOP)- CompTIA+. She also described in detail
        the application process for a postgraduate diploma/degree overseas. She talked about
        her college experience, graduation curriculum, and teaching learning pedagogy.   Final-

        ly, the session was opened up for questions, and each question was positively accepted
        and appropriately answered.
























       Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1                         13]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[14                     Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[INDUSTRIAL
                               INDUSTRIAL VISIT
                                                                          VISIT



        Title : Industrial Visit to Hyderabad

        Date: 12/04/2023-15/04/2023
        Batch- B.Sc Forensic science
        Semester- VI semester
        Total student participants- 54


        Objective:
        1.      To provide practical exposure to a state-of-the-art research and diagnostic facility
        in the field of DNA fingerprinting and diagnostics.

        2.  To interact with renowned scientists, researchers, and experts in the field of DNA
        fingerprinting


        Write up on the Programme


        Date: 12th and 15th April 2023
        An industrial visit was organised for the B.Sc. 6th Semester students total number of
        54 students, from April 12 to April 15, 2023, with the primary objective of providing

        them with practical insights into the field of DNA fingerprinting and diagnostics. The
        visit also offered an opportunity for the students to explore the rich cultural heritage and
        popular tourist attractions in Hyderabad.


        Day 1: Visit to the Centre for DNA Fingerprinting and Diagnostics (CDFD) On the first

        day of the industrial visit, the students visited the Centre for DNA Fingerprinting and
        Diagnostics (CDFD) in Hyderabad. The centre is renowned for its cutting-edge research
        and advancements in the field of DNA fingerprinting. The visit began with a guided

        tour, where the students were given an overview of the centre’s facilities and research
        activities.
        During the visit,  the  students  had  the  privilege  of witnessing  various  laboratories
        equipped with state-of-the-art technology used for DNA analysis. They interacted with
        the scientists and researchers at CDFD, who shared their knowledge and experiences

        regarding DNA fingerprinting techniques. The students learned about the applications of
        DNA fingerprinting in forensic science, paternity testing, and genetic research. The visit
        to CDFD provided a practical understanding of the concepts taught in their curriculum

        and exposed them to the latest developments in the field.


        Day 2 to Day 4: Tourist Attractions in Hyderabad
        Apart from the industrial visit, the students also had the opportunity to explore the cul-
        tural and historical landmarks of Hyderabad. The following popular tourist attractions

        were included in the itinerary:





       Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1                         15]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[Charminar: The iconic monument of Hyderabad, Charminar, was the first stop on the
        second day. Students marvelled at the architectural brilliance of this historical structure
        and learned about its cultural significance.



        Snow World: The visit to Snow World offered a unique experience to the students as they
        enjoyed the thrill of the snow-clad environment, engaging in various snow activities and
        rides. It provided a refreshing break from the scorching summer heat.



        Golconda Fort: Known for its grandeur and historical significance, Golconda Fort was a
        highlight of the tour. The students explored the massive fort complex, learned about its
        architectural features, and enjoyed panoramic views of the city from the top.



        Salarjung Museum: The Salarjung Museum houses an extensive collection of art, ar-
        tefacts, and historical items. The students had the opportunity to appreciate the diverse
        exhibits, including sculptures, paintings, textiles, and weaponry, showcasing India’s rich

        cultural heritage.


        Ramoji Film City: The visit to Ramoji Film City provided insights into the world of
        Indian cinema. The students witnessed various film sets, experienced behind-the-scenes

        activities, and learned about the filmmaking process.





















































                                                           16                   Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[INDUSTRIAL VISIT





        Title : Industrial Visit to RFSL, Mysore

        Date: 02/05/2023
        Batch- M.Sc Forensic science
        Semester- II semester
        Total student participants- 39


        Objective:
        1.  To Observe State-of-the-Art Equipment in RFSL
        2.  To provide Exposure to Different Forensic Disciplines



        Write up on the Programme


        Date: 12th and 15th April 2023
        The Industrial Visit to the Regional Forensic Science Laboratory (RFSL) in Mysore,

        Karnataka was organized for the M.Sc. Forensic Science 2nd semester students on 2nd
        of May 2023. The visit aimed to provide students with practical exposure to the vari-
        ous aspects of forensic science and its applications in real-world scenarios. The RFSL

        in Mysore is a well-established laboratory known for its advanced forensic facilities
        and expert professionals. The visit was headed by Dr. Suchita Rawat and Mr. Jeremiah
        Justus, Assistant Professor, Dept. of Forensic Science, Kristu Jayanti College (Autono-
        mous), Bengaluru.



        The industrial visit commenced at 9:00 AM with a warm welcome by the laboratory
        staff. The students were divided into smaller groups for better engagement and facilitat-
        ed learning. The visit comprised the following activities:



        1. Orientation and Introduction:
        The visit began with an orientation session where the laboratory’s objectives, functions,
        and the scope of forensic science were discussed. The students were introduced to the
        diverse forensic disciplines practised at the laboratory.

        2. Forensic Laboratory Tour:
        The students were taken on a comprehensive tour of the laboratory facilities. The tour
        covered various sections, including the DNA analysis, toxicology, fingerprinting, ballis-

        tics, and questioned documents sections. The students observed first-hand the state-of-
        the-art equipment and techniques used in each department.
        3. Demonstrations and Hands-on Experience:
        The laboratory staff conducted interactive demonstrations to illustrate the techniques
        and methodologies used in different forensic analyses. Students were given opportuni-

        ties to participate in simple hands-on activities, such as lifting fingerprints, analysing
        crime scene evidence, and observing microscopic slides.



       Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1                         17]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[4. Interaction with Forensic Experts:
        The students had the opportunity to interact with forensic scientists, experts, and ana-
        lysts. They were encouraged to ask questions and clarify doubts regarding various as-

        pects of forensic analysis, career prospects, and challenges faced in the field.
        5. Case Studies and Presentations:
        The laboratory personnel presented intriguing case studies, highlighting the role of fo-
        rensic science in solving complex crimes. Students were engaged in discussions to anal-

        yse the presented cases and understand the significance of forensic evidence in criminal
        investigations.
        6. Q & A Session and Feedback:
        A dedicated question and answer session was conducted, allowing students to seek fur-

        ther clarifications and gain insights into specific areas of interest. Feedback forms were
        distributed to the students to gather their thoughts and suggestions about the visit.


        The industrial visit to Regional Forensic Science Laboratory, Mysore, was an enriching

        and informative experience for the M.Sc. Forensic Science 2nd semester students. It
        provided them with valuable practical knowledge.




























































                                                           18                   Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[NA       TIONAL                      SCIENCE DA                                  Y
                  NATIONAL SCIENCE DAY




        On 28th February, the Deanery of sciences, Kristu Jayanti College Autonomous organ-

        ised various events commemorating National Science Day. This year, the theme was
        ‘Global science for global wellbeing’. As a part of its enterprise to conduct a wide range
        of extra-curricular programmes and activities to ignite the students on the development
        in science and technology.
        The department of Forensic science organised a range of events for the students of the

        undergraduate program. For the I year B.Sc. Forensic science students ‘Quizological’ -
        a quiz competition and Kaleidoscope - collage competition were conducted. For the II
        year B.Sc. Forensic science students ‘Quizological’ - a quiz competition and Point of

        order - elocution competition were conducted. For the III year B.Sc. Forensic science
        students ‘Quizological’ - a quiz competition was conducted. Students from undergradu-
        ate participated enthusiastically in these events. All the events were organised and con-
        ducted by students of postgraduate and undergraduate programs under the supervision
        of teachers. As a part of the valedictory program, the result of various events were an-

        nounced and winners were presented with certificates.


























































       Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1                        19]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[RESEARCH ARTICLES
















                                      Dna Extraction From Dandruff For
                      1               Dna     Ex   t r ac t ion Fr     om Da       ndr   uff F    or
                                                ic Ana
                                                               sis
                                                            l
                                                             y
                                      Genet
                                      Genetic Analysis


                      2               Sk  elet   al Dna       And Its Degr           adat     ion
                                      Skeletal Dna And Its Degradation







                                                                                                iess
                                                    ison Of W
                                                                      a
                                                                         lk
                                                                                s And Gr
                                      Compar
                                                                            er
                       3              Comparison Of Walkers And Griess
                                                                  a
                                                                    sis Of  Acquisit
                                                                                                ion Time
                                      Assay On The Basis Of  Acquisition Time
                                      Assa
                                              y On The B
                                                                         ac
                                                                               or Leading T
                                                                             t
                                                                    y F
                                                 t
                                                                                                      o
                                      Impac
                                                    Of F
                                                           amil
                      4               Impact Of Family Factor Leading To
                                                                                          hood
                                                                                         t
                                          imina
                                      Criminal Behaviour In Adulthood
                                      Cr
                                                                viour In Adul
                                                     l Beha


















                                                         20                       Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[DNA EXTRACTION


           FROM DANDRUFF FOR



           GENETIC ANALYSIS








             ABSTRACT


             Dandruff is a skin condition that caus-

             es the skin to peel. The most common
             cause of dandruff is dry skin, includ-
             ing other causes such as poor hygiene
             or illness. Some people may also de-

             velop dandruff due to allergies. Dead
             skin  is usually  shed from  the  scalp,
             but  with  dandruff,  the  removal  of
             these dead cells is usually faster and

             causes dead cells  to accumulate  on                      Image 1: Microscopic image of dandruff
             the scalp. If nucleated cells are found
             among these dead cells, DNA (deoxy-                 MATERIALS AND METHODS
             ribonucleic  acid) extraction may be

             possible. This article presents a pro-              1.Sample collection:
             tocol  for extracting  DNA from dan-                The dandruff flakes are collected from
             druff flakes collected from the scalp.              the scalp by gently shaking or brushing.
             The extracted DNA can be used for                   A sufficient amount of dandruff is col-

             a variety of genetic analyses, such as              lected for DNA extraction.
             genotyping, gene expression studies,
             and microbial community analysis.                    2.Cellulolysis:
             The method described here provides                  Caspa flakes are treated with a cellulol-

             a reliable and efficient way to obtain              ysis buffer containing detergent and pro-
             DNA from dandruff samples.                          teinase K. This buffer breaks cell mem-
             DNA  extraction  from  dandruff  can                branes and cleaves  proteins,  releasing
             provide information about individual                cell contents, including DNA.

             genetic characteristics, scalp microbi-
             al communities and potential genetic                3.Proteinase K Digestion:
             factors that influence dandruff.                    Proteinase K is added to the cell lysate




                                                           21
      Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[to digest proteins that may interfere with             and purification steps can affect the qual-
        DNA extraction. The sample is incubat-                 ity of extracted DNA.
        ed at a suitable temperature to facilitate
        melting.                                               CONCLUSION



        4.DNA precipitation:                                   Isolation of DNA  from dandruff is a useful
        Cold ethanol is added to the sample to                 and informative method to obtain genetic
        precipitate   DNA.  DNA forms visible                  material from scalp cells. The extracted

        strands  because  it  does  not  dissolve  in          DNA can be used for genetic studies, mi-
        ethanol.                                               crobial analysis and other molecular stud-
                                                               ies related to dandruff and scalp health.
        5.Centrifugation:

        The sample is centrifuged to collect the               FORENSIC            SIGNIFICANCE              OF
        DNA precipitate at the bottom of the tube              DANDRUFF
        while the liquid containing impurities is
        removed.                                               1.  Soon, only flake or hair will be needed

                                                                   to describe hair colour, the eyes, hair
        6. Washing and purification:                               and skin of the suspect and whether
        The DNA pellet is washed with ethanol                      they have a full or long face and even
        to remove residual impurities. For higher                  the shape of their earlobes.

        quality DNA, additional purification steps             2.  Caspa  particles  contain  a  significant
        can be performed using DNA purification                    proportion of nucleated cells in aggre-
        columns.                                                   gated  nucleated  corneocytes.  Caspa
                                                                   can detect the wearer of plain clothes

        7. DNA resuspension:                                       or a person who just used it.
        The DNA pellet is resuspended in a suit-               3.  Dandruff  can  also  occur  around  the
        able  buffer  or  distilled  water,  making  it            collars  and shoulders of clothing  on
        ready for later use.                                       the upper body.

                                                               4.  DNA extracted from dandruff can be
        DISCUSSION                                                 used for criminal profiling, creating a
                                                                   database.
        Isolation of DNA  from caspa is a valu-

        able source of genetic material for various
        research purposes. The method described
        here provides a relatively simple and ef-
        ficient  approach  to  extract  DNA  from

        caspase. Factors such as sampling, lysis








                                                           22
                                                                                 Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[REFERENCES



        1.  Dandruff as a potential source of DNA
            in forensic casework Lorente M;Entra-

            la C;Lorente JA; Alvarez JC;Villanue-
            va E; Budowle B;https://pubmed.ncbi.
            nlm.nih.gov/9670516/

        2.  CHAPTER-I. (n.d.). Retrieved  Au-
            gust 21, 2023, from https://aditya.

            ac.in/forensic-science/projects/Foren-
            sic%20Biology/Shifas_DNA%20ex-
            traction%20from%20dandruff.pdf

        3.  Image  1:  Wikipedia contributors.
            (2023).  Dandruff.  Wikipedia.  https://

            en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dandruff








































                Bhavya Kamath














                                                           23

       Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[SKELETAL DNA AND ITS


           ITS DEGRADATION











             INTRODUCTION                                        who share the same genetic material.


             DNA, also known as deoxyribonucle-                  In a crime scene, DNA can be ob-

             ic acid, is the genetic material pres-              tained  from  many  different  sources,
             ent in all living organisms. Most of                like blood, dead skin cells, semen,
             the DNA is present in the nucleus of                hair, and saliva. These pieces of ev-
             the cells of all animals and is a unique            idence  are then collected  and sent
             blueprint  that  helps in the  function-            to  forensic  laboratories  for  identifi-

             ing of the body. Some DNA can also                  cation. The DNA found at the scene
             be found outside the nucleus and is                 can help reduce or establish the in-
             called  mitochondrial  DNA, while                   volvement  or presence  of suspects

             the ones found inside the nucleus are               and can help narrow down the list. In
             called nuclear DNA.                                 cases where blood, hair, or saliva may
                                                                 not be available for the extraction of
             In the field of forensic science, DNA               DNA, forensic scientists may instead
             is a very crucial  piece of evidence.               use the skeletal remains to extract the

             DNA is used in processes such as                    DNA. This method is also used in the
             DNA profiling and DNA fingerprint-                  identification of unknown remains in
             ing, through which we are  able  to                 archaeological findings.

             identify the person who is the source
             of the DNA. Hence, DNA is useful                    DNA extraction from skeletal remains
             in identifying individuals as well as               is important for the purpose of identi-
             confirming their relation to a partic-              fication in cases related to mass disas-
             ular scene of crime or to a person. In              ters  and  unidentified  persons’  cases.

             the field of forensic science, DNA is               In cases where the body has been ex-
             regarded as an individual characteris-              posed to extreme environmental con-
             tic as it helps in the identification of            ditions and decay and the process of

             a single person. Each person’s DNA                  DNA extraction from tissues and bi-
             sequence is unique to them and can-                 ological fluids is not possible, we re-
             not be found in anyone else. The only               sort to the extraction of DNA from the
             exception for this statement is in the              skeletal remains, as these are the ones
             cases of identical twins


                                                           24

                                                                                   Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[often left behind in such cases. The ex-               skeletal  remains  have been  deposited

        traction of large quantities of DNA from               plays a crucial role in determining  the
        skeletal matter is a rather complicated pro-           rate at which the DNA molecules will de-
        cess, and there are many factors that can              grade. The less favourable the conditions

        affect the DNA extraction. Environmental               are, the faster they will degrade. Hence,
        factors play a huge role in the extraction             understanding  this process will help in-
        of DNA evidence, as they can adversely                 vestigators better collect  the samples
        affect the bone structure and its composi-             from the remains.
        tion. Even though the genetic material is

        protected by a hard structure, when com-               FACTORS  AFFECTING DNA EX-
        bined with environmental factors such as               TRACTION
        UV radiation, temperature, humidity, and

        microorganisms, the DNA gets degraded                  1. Temperature:
        over time.
                                                               High temperatures can promote chemical
        Although skeletal  DNA is much less                    reactions  that  can  degrade  DNA  mole-
        prone to destruction in comparison to its              cules. It can accelerate the breakdown of

        other sources, the degradation of the ge-              the genetic material. The various methods
        netic  material  is inevitable.  The quality           by which temperature can degrade DNA
        of the DNA obtained from the skeletal                  include processes like: Heat-Induced de-

        remains depends upon the conditions to                 naturation,
        which it could have been subjected. One                Thermal  hydrolysis and oxidative  dam-
        of the terms to keep in mind while study-              age. Heat-Induced Denaturation  occurs
        ing the DNA from skeletal  remains  is                 when the protein is heated, and this heat-
        “taphonomy.” Taphonomy is the study of                 ing  causes thermal  motion  and other

        postmortem changes to human remains.                   factors to break down the structure  of
        It is a discipline related to palaeontology            the protein, resulting in its denaturation.
        and studies the  process of fossilisation.             Thermal degradation of genetic material

        This process could  also encompass  the                can occur above 190°C. Thermal degra-
        decay of soft tissue, the deterioration and            dation of DNA at high temperatures in-
        separation of the bones, and alterations in            cludes the breaking down of the covalent
        the organism’s composition after burial.               bonds within the DNA strands. High tem-
        Various environmental factors can lead to              peratures increase the rate of hydrolysis,

        different  levels  of  DNA  preservation  in           and the water molecules interact with the
        different skeletons as well as in the same             DNA sugar-phosphate backbone, leading
        bones within a particular skeleton.                    to its degradation.  Oxidative  damage  to

        Therefore, the environment in which the                the DNA occurs, as the name suggests,








                                                           25

        Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[due  to  the oxidation  reaction  that  takes          4. Oxygen levels:

        place as the temperature rises. The DNA
        is oxidised, leading to the production of              The oxygen molecules participate in oxi-
        free radicals that damage the DNA struc-               dative reactions and can modify the DNA
        ture. Hence, it results in the degradation             backbone and create lesions in the DNA

        of the genetic material.                               strand. This then leads to further degra-
                                                               dation as well as helical distortion, which
        2. Microorganisms:                                     can complicate genetic analysis. Oxygen
                                                               also influences the rate and extent of de-

        Microorganisms  in  soil  can  release  en-            composition  by microorganisms.  Soils
        zymes that separate and breakdown nat-                 that have higher oxygen levels lead to
        ural materials, including DNA. The mi-                 higher rates of DNA degradation.
        croorganisms  do not destroy  the  DNA

        directly; instead, they digest the protein             These  are some of the  factors  that  lead
        components of the bones, making the                    to the destruction of the genetic materi-
        skeletal  DNA more susceptible  to de-                 al from the skeletal remains. A forensic
        struction. These proteins can increase the             scientist must keep these in mind if they

        rate of breakdown of the phosphodiester                wish to collect  a feasible DNA sample
        bonds that hold the DNA strands together.              for examination. DNA analysis is a very
        Both endogenous and exogenous organ-                   crucial part of forensic investigation and
        isms contribute to the decomposition pro-              must be handled with the utmost care.

        cess. Hence, microorganisms play a huge                Since a mistake on the forensic expert’s
        part in the degradation of genetic materi-             part can lead to severe consequences for
        al.                                                    those involved in the case, One wrongful
                                                               conviction can ruin the lives of many.

        3. Moisture:
                                                               REFERENCES
        The presence of moisture in the environ-
        ment can lead to the biological decompo-               1.  Latham, K. E., & Miller, J. J. (2018,

        sition of DNA. The water molecules take                    October 8). DNA recovery and anal-
        part  in  hydrolytic  reactions  that  lead  to            ysis from skeletal  material  in mod-
        the fragmentation and modification of the                  ern forensic contexts. Forensic Sci-
        DNA molecules. If there is more humid-                     ence  Research, 15(1), 51-59. https://

        ity in the area of the skeletal remains, the               www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/
        greater the likelihood of DNA damage.                      PMC6427720/












                                                           26

                                                                                 Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[2.  H.E. McKiernan, P.B. Danielson. (2017)
            Molecular Diagnostics, Molecu lar Di-
            agnostics, Molecular Diagnostic Appli-
            cations  in Forensic Science,3.  https://

            www.sciencedirect.com/science/arti-
            cle/abs/pii/B9780128029718000225

        3.  Iskander,  V. (2022, Sept 12). Role  of
            DNA in Forensic Science.  azolife-
            sciences.  https://www.azolifesciences.

            com/article/Role-of-DNA-in-Forensic-
            Science.aspx

        4.  Behrensmeyer,  A. K., Denys, C., &
            Brugal, J.-P. (2018). What is taphono-
            my and what is not? Taylor & Francis

            Online.  https://www.tandfonline.com/
            doi/full/10.1080/08912963.2018.14329
            19
        5.  Karni, M., Zidon, D., Polak, P., Za-
            levsky,  Z.,  &  Shefi,  O.(2012).  Ther-

            mal  degradation  of DNA. DNA Cell
            Biol.  32(6),298-301. https://pubmed.
            ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/23621849/#:~:tex-

            t=We%20find%20that%20under%20
            dry,for%20different%20applied%20
            partial%20pressures.

        6.  Shef, O. (2013).  Thermal  degrada-
            tion of DNA.  DNA and cell biology.

            32(6). 1-4. https://www.eng.biu.ac.il/
            shefio/files/2012/05/thermal-degrada-
            tion-of-dna.pdf










                       Pavithra Manoj










                                                           27
       Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[COMPARISON OF WALKERS


       AND GRIESS ASSAY ON THE



      BASIS OF  ACQUISITION TIME









        ABSTRACT


        Gunshot Residue (GSR) analysis is one                  According  to the  analysis  using Mun-
        of the major steps to be done in case of               sell’s Chart not only the intensity of co-

        firearm investigation. The study focused               lour but also the reactivity of both assays
        mainly on the analysis of simulated GSR                based on the colour they produced as re-
        samples collected from different surfaces              sult on gauze cloth with sample, sample

        using Walker’s, and Griess Assay by tak-               collected from the surface based on the
        ing acquisition time as a parameter. Gun-              time chart and different clothes were also
        shot residue helps to determine whether                analysed. And also, a time period chart
        a shooting has taken place, whether the                was prepared. It was found that  Griess
        suspect  himself  has done the  shooting,              test has greater  reactivity  with older

        whether shooting has done with the sus-                samples than Walker’s test. From my re-
        pected firearm and the GSR distribution                search it was also found that proper pres-
        pattern will help to establish the distance            ervation plays a pivotal role in the yield-

        from muzzle end to target.                             ing of good quality results.


        The result of our study was the detection              KEYWORDS
        of nitrite residue will be more in freshly             Gunshot  residue,  Walker’s Test,  Griess
        collected samples than the samples which               Test, Acquisition time, Munsell chart.

        are tested after a particular period of time
        and also Griess test was comparatively                 CHAPTER I
        reactive with old samples than Walker’s.

        The tests are based on chromophoric re-                1. INTRODUCTION
        actions and Walker’s test gave red colour
        and Griess test gave pink colour. The in-              1.1 BALLISTICS
        tensity of the colour was analysed using               Ballistics is the study of firearms and am-
        Munsell’s chart.                                       munition. Calvin Hooker Goddard








                                                           28
                                                                                  Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[is  known  as  the  father  of  modern  fire-        particular firearm or ammunition. There
        arm identification. There are mainly three             is  one  more  classification  called  trans-
        subdivisions that come under ballistics                lational  ballistics  which deals with the
        and they are internal  ballistics,  external           study of projectiles between external bal-

        ballistics, and terminal ballistics. Internal          listics and terminal ballistics. It involves
        ballistics  deals  with the  study of things           the gap or time period between external
        happening  inside an ammunition.  It in-               and terminal ballistics. Dealing with fire-
        cludes the firing mechanism which begins               arms, first primitive firearm is known as

        with cocking, chambering, locking, load-               cannon lock which was later suppressed
        ing, unlocking, extraction, ejection. It in-           by matchlock and this was first automat-
        volves the whole mechanism that begins                 ic firearm which brings fire into the pan
        from loading till the ejection of projectile           placed of gunpowder to ignite with a sin-

        out of the muzzle end of a firearm. Exter-             gle pull of a trigger and then came wheel
        nal ballistics deals with the events that are          lock and this was suppressed by flint lock
        happening outside the firearm. It involves             and later  came  percussion cap which
        all the mechanisms of a projectile which               was called the modern primitive firearm.

        leaves  the  muzzle  end  and  lasts  until  it        Earlier most of the firearms used muzzle
        reaches the target thereby the path trav-              loading  mechanism  and now there  are
        elled by projectile, range, shape of trajec-           breech  loading  firearms  too. The  exam-
        tory, spin of bullet, drift, angle of fire all         ination of arms and ammunition is essen-

        comes under this category. It also deals               tial  in reconstruction of a crime scene.
        with the motion of projectiles in an open
        atmosphere. The terminal ballistics deals              1.2 FORENSIC BALLISTICS
        with the effect of a projectile on hitting a           Forensic ballistics deals with the study of

        target and based on this factor there is an-           firearms  and  ammunition  and  its  appli-
        other  classification  called  wound  ballis-          cation in legal perspective. It deals with
        tics. Wound ballistics means the effect of             the investigation of a shooting scene and
        a projectile on hitting a living organism              it requires knowledge in firearms, exter-

        or target and if a projectile is hitting on            nal  ballistics,  internal  ballistics,  wound
        a non-living thing then its effect is called           ballistics etc. Shooting deals with serious
        terminal  ballistics.  When a projectile               crimes like murders, kidnapping, robbery,
        strikes the human body, it depresses and               attempted murders, terrorism and this of-

        compresses the skin, flush and the bone                ten leads to death or serious injuries to
        and thereby leaving permanent or tempo-                the victim.  The court seeks the help of
        rary damage to the tissue and this plays               experts in ballistics to reach a conclusion
        an important role in identification of that            and thereby  ensuring  that  not a single

        uiouyufyfiyoiiouryiotuiygukhfghjkhytgf








                                                           29

        Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[innocent person is punished and the cul-               identification of the weapon and thereby
        prit  is to be found guilty.  The shooting             solving about 95% cases. The high veloc-
        location  provides evidence  that  help  us            ity rifle and automatic and semiautomat-
        to establish corpus delicti, link criminal             ic  firearms,  imprint  identifiable  breech

        victim and crime scene, appraise the pat-              face marks on cartridges fired from them.
        tern,  find  modus  operandi,  identify  sus-          When the chamber portion has some de-
        pect,  help  in  reconstruction  of incident.          fects then it would imprint some markings
        The identification of firearms which have              on the tubular portion of the cartridge.

        released bullet or projectile, fired incrim-           The linkage of buckshot with shotgun is
        inating cartridges is the most important               of great importance in forensic ballistics
        aspect of forensic ballistics. When a trig-            as in India. Nowadays people make use
        ger is pulled it will cause the firing pin             of shotguns to commit crimes because of

        to strike at the base of cartridge causing             the ease of availability of firearms. The
        the igniting of primer and it further leads            spreading of these pellets helps in estab-
        to the ignition of propellants and thereby             lishing the suspect to target distance.
        causing the build-up of gases and creates

        a pressure which will finally leads to the             The  stereomicroscopic  examination  of
        expulsion of projectile out of the firearm             bullets helps in establishing class charac-
        through  muzzle  end.  While  a  cartridge             teristics and a comparison microscope is
        case passes through a barrel it is forced to           used to compare both test bullets and the

        face the breach end and certain individu-              evidence (bullet fired collected from vic-
        al marks are being imparted into the case              tim or crime scene) to see whether both
        and projectile and thereby these individ-              bullets have same individual  and class
        uals characteristics helps in the identifi-            characteristics  and  thereby  linking  the

        cation of a firearm and play an important              crime scene to the suspect.
        role in firearm investigation. The position,
        size and the general shape of a firing pin,
        extractor and ejector marks on cartridges              1.3 TRANSFER OF GSR

        are the class characteristics of a firearm             The transfer of GSR occur in two ways
        and the finer marks on a projectile or car-            they are,
        tridge case constitute individual features
        of a firearm. No two firearms, even of the             1.  Primary  Transfer:  occurs immediate-

        same make and model, produced one af-                      ly after shooting has taken place and
        ter the other can also differ from each oth-               mostly deposits on the hands of the
        er and thereby making it stands out. The                   shooter  mainly  the  index  and  thumb
        firing pin mark alone had helped in                        fingers and also the web region. GSR

                                                                   also gets deposited on other surfaces








                                                           30

                                                                               Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[like cloth, face, person standing next

             to the shooter, sometimes  inside of
             ears and nostrils.
         2.  Secondary Transfer: Transfer of GSR

             to another surface and usually it oc-
             curs without direct contact between
             the shooter/donor and the target/sur-
             face.

         The distribution of GSR is influenced by
         various factors such as the firearm used,                Figure 1.2: Collection of Gunshot residue

         the surface, environmental  factors like                           using Swabbing method.
         indoor or outdoor, airflow, humidity, rain
         and distance.                                           The collected  swab was then placed in
         There  are  different  methods  employed                a zip lock bag and analysis was done on
         for collection of samples, each collection              freshly in a zip lock bag and analysis was

         techniques are important when it comes                  done  on  freshly  collected  samples  and
         into analysis. The methods used are tape                according  to the  time chart  after  acqui-
         lifting method, swabbing method, vacu-                  sition of GSR, further analysis was per-

         um lifting method, washing method etc.                  formed. Two different ways were used for
                                                                 the analysis of the sample; one is by per-
         1.  Tape lifting method: An adhesive tape               forming analysis on the gauze cloth with

            is pressed on the  suspected  areas  of              GSR according to the time chart and next
            hands of the person it is then stuck to              way is by performing analysis on samples
            a glass slide.

         2.  Vacuum lifting method: Suitable meth-
            od for collection of GSR from clothes.

         3.  Washing method:  The hands of the

            person are  washed using a diluted
            solution of HNO3. It is collected in a
            flat tray.

         4.  Swabbing Method: A clean gauze cloth
            moistened  with  5%  HNO3 is  taken,

            and the site suspected of containing
            GSR is swabbed.

         Swabbing method is used in our study to
         collect the gunshot residue from the sur-               Figure 1.3: different GSR analysis methods

         face.






                                                           31

         Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[collected  directly  from the surface ac-               3.  likewise  presence  of  barium  gives  a
       cording to the time period that we have                     red or brown colour.
       set. And also, analysis is done on different
       fabric materials.                                       1.5 INSTRUMENTS USED  TO DE-

       The Analysis method of GSR is mainly                    TECT ORGANIC GSR
       of two types, advanced method and con-                  8.  Gas Chromatography- Mass  Spec-
       ventional method. Conventional methods                      trometry (GC-MS): combines features
       include colour-based analysis and instru-                   of both gas Chromatography and Mass

       mentation.                                                  Spectrometry.  The  operation  of GC-
                                                                   MS comprises the following steps;

       1.4 COLORIMETRIC TESTS                                  a.  Sample  preparation:  dissolved  or di-
       3.  Dermal Nitrate Test: .25% solution of                   luted  sample in a solvent  is injected

           Diphenyl benzidine  (now Diphenyl-                      into the inlet port.
           amine) in conc. Sulphuric acid is used.             b.  Vaporisation: The liquid sample is va-
           The  presence  of nitrate  produces a                   porised and it becomes a gas.
           deep blue coloration.                               c.  Separation:  The sample is carried

       4.  Walker’s  Test: 5% 2 naphthylamine                      through the column by the mobile
           4,8-disulphonic  acid  and 20% acetic                   phase. Due to  their  own chemistry,
           acid, these are the reagents used. Pres-                different substances travel at different
           ence of nitrite produces a bright red                   speeds through the column. This caus-

           spot.                                                   es their separation at different time
       5.  Griess Test: This test is similar to the            d.  Detection: The separated sample then
           Walker’s test  but  instead  of 2  naph-                enters into a detector, here it is the
           thylamine 4,8- disulphonic acid, naph-                  mass spectrometer. It then detects the

           thylamine is used. The nitrite residue                  retention time.
           will produce orange spots.                          9.  High Performance Liquid Chromatog-
       6.  Modified  Griess  Test:  Procedure  is                  raphy (HPLC): Works by the principle
           same as that of Griess test. But it in-                 of adsorption and also partition chro-

           cludes a step of using filter paper which               matography. High pressure is used.
           is sprayed with 2 naphthylamine sul-                10.  Thin Layer Chromatography
           fanilic and citric acid. Positive result                (TLC): Works by the concept of sepa-
           will give a pink colour.                                ration of each component at different

       7.  Sodium Rhodizonate  Test: Saturated                     time
           solution  of  sodium  rhodizonate  and              11.  Raman          Spectroscopy:        Method
           0.1 N HCL are the reagents. Presence                    which uses the molecule’s vibrational
           of lead particles  will produce purple                  mode. Other states such as rotational

           colour,                                                 states are also detected.








                                                           32


                                                                                 Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[1.6 INSTRUMENTS USED  TO DE-                            lead is observed
        TECT INORGANIC GSR

                                                                3.  X-ray fluorescence: A useful technique
        12.  Atomic Absorption  Spectrometry                        to carry out both qualitative and quan-
            (AAS): Nanogram and picogram rang-                      titative detection of gunshot residue. It

            es are detected.  Works based on the                    is easy to implement and is cheap when
            factor that the element when excited                    compared to. The technique as well as
            will emit the wavelength it absorbed.                   operation  is simple,  convenient  and
        13.  Neutron          Activation       Analysis             also reliable results given by it make it
            (NAA): Antimony and Barium are de-                      a very useful method. Apart from this

            tected. Bombarding neutrons give ra-                    Autoradiography, Photoluminescence,
            dioactive barium and radioactive anti-                  lead isotopy, emission spectroscopy
            mony.                                                   and polarography can also be used.

        14.  Scanning Electron Microscope-En-
            ergy Dispersive X-ray (SEM-EDX):                    In this experiment we are also performing
            Quick and non- destructive  method.                 analysis on different types of cloth apart
            Barium, lead, potassium etc are detect-             from the gauze cloth we commonly used
            ed.                                                 for collection. It is because the GSR can

                                                                be present on various clothes if the tar-
        Advanced  method  in GSR analysis  in-                  get is a person. The types of clothes also
        cludes the following;                                   play an important role in the detection of

        For OGSR detection;                                     GSR, because the persistence of GSR on
        1.  Cyclic Voltammetry (CV): detect oxi-                a cloth is really dependent on the material
            dation and reduction.                               of cloth.
        2.  Nitrite test based on amperometry:
            Measured dropping current in mercury                1.7  THE  FABRICS  USED IN  THIS

            electrode at constant time.                         ANALYSIS


        For IGSR detection;                                     15.  Cotton gauze cloth:  Cotton gauze

        1.  Infrared Photography: In case of gun-                   cloth  is the  traditional  item  used in
            shot residue being present on dark co-                  every discipline of forensic science to
            loured cloth use of infrared photogra-                  collect evidence. It’s very absorbent in
            phy reveals its presence.                               nature and mostly does not interfere
        2.  Soft X-rays Radiography: Lead  met-                     with the analysis.

            al is opaque to X-rays. So, use of                  16.  Linen: It is a flax-based textile. It is
            soft X-ray detects a hole as a gunshot                  similar to cotton but takes a long time
            wound hole if the presence of opaque                    to harvest. It’s commonly used to









                                                           33

        Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[to make shirts, pants, other dresses, pil-              the presence, and those techniques are
       low cases, napkins etc. That means, it’s                the one we already discussed, that is the
       a widely used cloth material. It also has               colour-based tests, several  instrumenta-
       absorbance similar to cotton.                           tions, IR photography, use of alternative

       17.  Jute: It is a plant fibre. It is soft and          light sources etc.
           shiny and is widely available.  Being
           plant  fibres  jute  have  a  high  absor-          Since GSR being the major evidence to
           bance capacity. It readily absorbs wa-              prove and disprove a shooting, the analy-

           ter and also other substances but dries             sis is also at an important scale. Analysis
           quickly.                                            of GSR has many uses, but altogether it
       18.  Wool: Wool is made from animal fi-                 can be divided into two, the first one is to
           bre, mostly from fleece and sheep. It’s             identify whether a firearm has been used

           comparatively heavier than other cloth              recently by a person and the second is to
           materials. Wool has more absorbance                 determine  the  muzzle to  target  distance
           capacity. Since it is heavier with much             based on the GSR pattern formed. In this
           more thick threads, it absorbs more.                study we mainly focus on the reactivity
                                                               of Walker’s test, Griess test and Modified

       Presence of GSR on clothes is very com-                 Griess test. Also the effect of acquisition
       mon. It gets transferred by various ways;               time on the reactivity of these tests and
                                                               also analysis is done on different fabrics.

       If the target is a human, GSR will be pres-
       ent on the body of the victim as well as                In this study we mainly focus on the com-
       his/her  clothes.  Definitely  on  the  hands           parison of two tests based on the acquisi-
       as well as clothes of the shooter. There                tion time. It is mainly done by collecting

       are possibilities of transferring of GSR to             the simulated sample on a gauze cloth and
       the clothes of a person standing near to                by directly collecting the sample from the
       the shooter if any. Clothes can be used to              surface at a specific time. In a crime scene
       clean the firearm, in this case GSR can be              we encounter different situations like get-

       found on the cloth.                                     ting GSR from floor, wall, clothes, glass
       Studies report that GSR stays up to seven               surfaces etc. The surface used in this study
       hours on a shooter’s skin, whereas it can               is glass. Glass is a transparent, solid, brit-
       be present on clothes up to a month when                tle material made by raw materials such

       it is kept undisturbed. Usually, gun pow-               as sand, soda ash and limestone. Glass is
       der stain can be seen easily on light co-               made by the melting of these materials at
       loured clothes, but if the residue is pres-             high temperatures.  At high temperature
       ent on dark or blood-stained clothes then               glass is similar to solid and when cooled

       it requires several techniques to reveal                down it acts like solid. Some other prop








                                                           34

                                                                               Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[erties  of glass  are  dimensional  stability,           hen sprayed by 15% Acetic acid. Orange
        heat resistance, low thermal conductivity,              colour  indicated  the  presence  of  nitrite

        electrical insulation etc. GSR can also be              residues. The modified Griess test results
        used to determine  the  distance  between               show  different  colour  intensities  within
        target and the shooter. It is a major aspect            different fabrics with different firing dis-

        that should be discussed in detail. It is of            tances. The more/less intensity of the co-
        great forensic relevance as it is the ma-               lour shows more/less presence of GSR on
        jor way to prove or disprove the fact of                fabrics.  The  information  obtained  from
        shooting at a particular distance claimed               this study was that the persistence  of
        by either the shooter or the victim. It can             GSR residues on different fabrics cannot

        be done by analysing the pattern  distri-               depend upon the variable firing distanc-
        bution on the target clothing or the target             es rather it depends on the texture of the
        surface.  Another way to determine  the                 fabrics. As the distance was increased the

        distance between the target and the victim              GSR intensity was decreased, which was
        is based on the firearm wounds.                         observed by this research.(3)
        diluted solution of HNO3.
                                                                Priya Shrivastava, V.K studied “on Gun-
        CHAPTER II                                              shot residue detection technologies”  in

                                                                2011. This study aimed at finding differ-
        2. REVIEW OF LITERATURE                                 ent  instrumentation  and  analysis  meth-
                                                                ods to detect the presence of residue, its

        Muneeba Butt, M.S published an article                  constituents, elemental form etc. It cov-
        on “Trace  analysis  of Gunshot Residue                 ers almost all techniques and culminates
        on different fabrics using locally manu-                the merits and demerits of these analysis
        factured  ammunition” in the year 2016.                 methods. This paper helps the scientist to
        The objective of the study was to anal-                 know about the advanced tools in finding

        yse the  composition  of GSR and  they                  GSR analysis. (14)
        used scanning electron microscopy with
        energy dispersive X-ray spectroscopy to                 R.K Mishra focused on “The involvement

        look into the elemental structure and the               of GSR in a crime case” in 2022. GSR
        composition was analysed using different                plays an important role in linking a crime
        chemical tests producing different inten-               to crime scene, victim and suspect. In this
        sities of colours. For Modified Griess Test             study they try to seek answers for two hy-
        15% Glacial acetic acid solution, 0.5 gm                potheses and one is whether the suspect

        sulphanilic acid, 0.28 gm alpha naphthol                has shooted at a specific site and whether
        in 100 ml methanol  was required.  The                  the suspect has not shooted ie; whether he
        fabrics were soaked in these solutions and              is innocent or not. In this study they took









                                                           35

      Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[a  case  and  found GSR residue  on the                 the hands of the shooter and to differen-
       hands of a male (shooter) who was found                 tiate  it  from the  environmental  factors
       dead beside women. So the analysis pro-                 by using solid phase microextraction gas
       vided  clues  to  the  investigation  officer           chromatography  mass spectrometry  and

       that  the  male  had  done  the  firing  and            also using SEM-EDX which is a non-de-
       killed the women and he himself shot to                 structive technique. Here the samples are
       death. Their case review study proved the               collected  from the hands of the shooter
       important GSR analysis in criminal dis-                 using adhesive carbon aluminium  stubs

       putes. (11)                                             and blank samples were collected before
                                                               shooting. Organic residues were analysed

       Siti Nurhazlin  Jaluddin focused on                     first in order to minimise any potential loss
       “The preliminary evaluation of GSR us-                  of organic residue. From a single sample

       ing 3-Aminophenol  as a substitute  in                  almost 100 known organic residues were
       Modified Griess test” in 2021. The aim of               detected. This result showed the success-
       the study was to find a rapid test instead of           ful application of these techniques in this
       Modified Griess test where heating is not               field. (5)

       required and also less toxic and less ex-
       pensive substance used as a main reagent                Kelsey E Seyfang focused on “Glass con-
       compared  to  the  one  used  in  Modified              taining gunshot residues and particles of
       Griess test. The rapid Griess test reagent              industrial and occupational origins and its

       was prepared  using  28  gm  of  3–Amin-                evaluation for traces of GSR ‘’. The aim
       ophenol in 100 ml methanol was added                    of the study was to find Glass containing
       to 5 gm of sulphanilic acid solution. And               GSR  from the samples collected  from
       this was further stored in a sealed bottle.             different  locations  which  were  mixed

       The result obtained from the test was the               with  firework  residues.  The  analysis  of
       presence or formation of orange colour in               the  sample was done using SEM-EDS.
       presence of nitrite residue and also the in-            Aluminium pin stubs covered in carbon
       tensity of orange colour formed by Rapid                adhesive were used to collect  the sam-

       Griess test is more compared to Modified                ples. This work highlighted the particles
       Griess test and this was analysed using a               that contribute a level of particles which
       calorimeter. (17)                                       is indistinguishable from GSR and in par-
                                                               ticular glass containing GSR. If in a sam-

       Ellen Goudsmits focused on “The analy-                  ple more amount of KClO3 is found then
       sis of organic and inorganic gunshot res-               it shows that the source is from a firework
       idue from a single sample” in 2019. The                 and not from ammunition and also when
       main aim of the study was to detect GSR                 the amount of Mg is considerably more

       residue from a single sample collected                  than it shows the contribution of it towards








                                                           36

                                                                               Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[fireworks  to  produce  colours  which  are             as trace in nasal mucus by GFAAS” IN
        absent in ammunition. This study proved                 2016. The objective of this study was to

        that fireworks do not appear to be capable              detect  the  presence  of gunshot residue
        of generating particles that would resem-               from nasal aperture since the mucus layer
        ble glass containing GSR. (15)                          inside the nasal cavity trap the entry of

        Joshua Hallet focused on “Examination                   foreign particle and also if we are collect-
        of gunshot residue arising from shotgun                 ing sample from the hands of the shooter
        cartridges containing steel, bismuth or                 the chance of detecting residue would be
        tungsten pellets” in 2019. The aim of the               comparatively  very lower after 8 hours
        study was to determine GSR constituents                 where in former one the residing time is

        from a shotgun as the cases of suicide and              larger and another big advantage is that
        homicide has shown an increased use of                  it can be used as a complementary evi-
        shotguns which is easily available com-                 dence instead of the one collected from

        pared to rifled firearm and this was studied            hand and the chance of instrumental con-
        in Australia.  The collection  was carried              tamination is lower. Here they collect the
        out in 2 days and a 12 inch convention-                 samples from the nasal aperture using a
        al  pin stubs with carbon adhesive  tape                cotton  swab moistened with EDTA and
        was used to collect the residue from the                it was analysed using Graphite Furnace

        barrel, base of primer cap, the firing pin              Atomic  Absorption Spectrometry  and
        position  and the  shattered  residue  from             searched for Sb, Pb, Ba. They even col-
        the surface. Pb, Sb, Ba particles obtained              lected  blank samples too.  The result of

        from a steel shotgun were classified ac-                their study was that the concentration that
        cording to a defined standard system and                we found from the nasal region is low-
        it was counted using the Zeiss instrument.              er than the one found from hands of the
        The study showed that when a steel shot                 shooter but the detection of residue was
        was fired it ejected Fe particles in GSR at             possible and could be used as comple-

        the breech end and not from muzzle end                  mentary evidence in future. (10)
        and in Bi or W shot it did not produce Fe
        residue discharge from muzzle end but in                Bailey, Casanova, and Bufkin conduct-

        breach portion and this study also showed               ed a study on “A Method for Enhancing
        that the particles found in GSR residue is              Gunshot  Residue Patterns on Dark and
        not  alone  formed  from  the  ammunition               Multi-coloured  Fabrics Compared  with
        but also from barrel and this was clearly               Modified Griess Test ‘’. The microscopic
        understood  by detecting  presence  of Fe               GSR particles are enhanced under infra-

        from Bi shot. (7)                                       red photography and Modified Griess test
                                                                was performed to compare with patterns
        Chavez focused on “The analysis of GSR                  developed by treating Sodium hypochlo









                                                           37


      Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[rite. The GSR patterns developed as a re-               GSR distribution of any element is acces-
       sult of MGT were measured and photo-                    sible for the XRF method.(21)
       graphed. Likewise, the pattern developed
       after treatment with Sodium hypochlorite                Kersh, Childers,  Justice  and Karim fo-

       was also measured and photographed.                     cused on the topic “Detecting GSR  on
       Both were compared. In conclusion, ac-                  Dark Coloured Clothing Prior to Chem-
       cording to the study, use of sodium hy-                 ical Analysis”. This study is mainly con-
       pochlorite from enhancing GSR patterns                  cerned  about  the  detection  of  GSR us-

       provide the investigator an option for                  ing alternate light sources (ALS). Study
       evaluating both dark and multi-coloured                 was preceded by using three dark fabrics
       fabrics that can be bleached; if the fabric             collected from three different shirts. The
       cannot be bleached, then enhancing with                 ALS used by them for the study was mod-

       IR photography and Modified Griess test                 el: MIS400. AS a result of the study the
       are opted.(20)                                          wavelength 415 and below gave little to
                                                               no illumination for GSR but a high one for
       Berendes, Neimke, Schumacher and                        the surroundings. 445 nm provided great

       Barth conducted a study on “A Versatile                 distinction  between  GSR and surround-
       Technique  for the Investigation  of GSR                ing. GSR appeared as bright neon green
       Patterns on Fabrics and other Surfaces”.                against a black background. 455 nm and
       They conducted study on samples such as                 475 nm also gave good contrast. In CSS

       cloths, foils, human tissue etc. The sam-               filter  the  GSR  fluorescence  as  yellow/
       ples of clothing were stretched on a frame              gold against a dark orange background.
       and kept in place by clamps. The cloth                  495 nm showed the same result as CSS
       samples were analysed by Midex M. Hu-                   but appeared against a brown background.

       man tissue required a special type of hold-             500 nm caused GSR to fluoresce red on
       er to enable cooling during measurement.                black, purple or orange background and
       A gel-filled cryo-table was used for this               so on. They analysed till 630 nm and it
       purpose. The M-XRF method combines                      gave a very poor result with little to no

       resolution, speed, detectable  elements,                contrast between GSR and background.
       sample preparation etc as is very useful                In this particular study they proved that
       in GSR detection from different surfaces                while using ALS, different fabric blends
       like cloths, foil, pork skin. Based on this             had varying results on visualisation  of

       study the Spectro Midex M is a prominent                GSR and gave results at particular wave-
       tool for GSR analysis and shooting range                lengths.(22)
       estimation. This method can be used in-
       stead of the other common technique as it               Brozek-Mucha Zuzanna, 2017 focused on

       is a non- destructive method and access to              the topic “Trends in Analysis of Gunshot








                                                           38


                                                                                 Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[Residue for Forensic Purposes”. Study                   detect the nitrite residue from gloves us-
        focused on analysis using SEM coupled                   ing modified Griess test and calorimeter

        with Energy dispersive X-ray. Conducted                 instead  of SEM-EDX. SEM-EDX was
        study on analysis of both organic and in-               somewhat  complicated because  it  re-
        organic components of gunshot residue.                  quires  the  transfer  of  residue  from  one

        According to the study, the solid particles             surface to another and it would be diffi-
        from the unburnt or partially burnt propel-             cult to transfer using a tape lifting meth-
        lant particle distribution pattern  around              od from a fabric. They used a Modified
        the  wound  and  the  on-target’s clothing              Griess  test to determine  nitrite  residue
        paved the way to estimate  the shooting                 from gloves and it was placed over a cal-

        range. It also provided information about               orimeter and a pink colour was obtained
        vibrational  spectroscopy,  which  offers               as a result. Their statistical study showed
        great opportunity in the analysis of both               that the chances of finding nitrite residue

        organic  and inorganic  components  of                  from the gloves from both left and right
        GSR that are usually mixed together.(23)                hand would be the same and the chances
                                                                of the residue being deposited and settled
        Mahony and  Wang conducted  a study                     for a long time would be greater in gloves
        about “Electrochemical Detection of Gun-                palm  and  finger  region  than  hands  of  a

        shot Residue for Forensic Analysis”. The                shooter which could be easily removed by
        study focused on the use of electrochemi-               washing. The result of the study proved
        cal devices for the detection of GSR. They              the link between gloves worn during

        used Anodic  Stripping  Voltammetry  for                shooting to the crime scene, suspect, vic-
        the detection of the metallic components                tim and also modified Griess test could be
        of GSR. They also relied on SEM/EDX,                    employed in crime scene investigation to
        Raman Spectroscopy and AAS/ICP-OES                      provide a vital clue in GSR analysis. (12)
        for chemometric treatment. In this study

        they are showcasing electrochemical de-                 Abdul Halim, Ahmad, Hooi, and Jasmani
        vices as one of the most effective and fast-            conducted a study on “Analysis of Gun-
        er methods for the detection of GSR. This               shot Residue Deposited on Cloth”. Chem-

        article also reviewed the recent improve-               ical analysis was done using the Modified
        ments in the electrochemical  detection                 Griess test. The study provided informa-
        system with chemometric analysis.(24)                   tion about the presence of GSR on target
                                                                cloth and the detection of GSR on target
        Azie Azyanti Mohd, Ratae, S.T focused                   cloth up to a distance of 15 inch and also

        on  “Colourimetric  based  detection  of                about the possibility of finding GSR on
        GSR on gloves worn during shooting” in                  different cloth material with increase in
        2019. The objective of the study was to









                                                           39


     Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[time.  Also provided information  about                3.2.2 OBJECTIVES
        the  determination  of distance  between
        shooter and target based on the GSR dis-               To compare the reactivity of Griess test
        tribution pattern on target cloth.                     with  the  simulated  sample  collected  on
                                                               gauze cloth taking acquisition time as pa-

        CHAPTER - III                                          rameter.
                                                               1.  To compare the reactivity of Walkers
        3. METHODOLOGY                                             test with the simulated sample collect-
                                                                   ed on gauze cloth  taking acquisition

        3.1 PROBLEM STATEMENT                                      time as parameter.
                                                               2.  To compare  the  reactivity  of Griess
        The study emphasises on the reactivity of                  and Walkers test with the sample col-

        GSR with Griess and Walkers test taking                    lected on different fabric material.
        time of acquisition as a parameter and to
        find  whether  the  fabric  material  affects          3.3 PROCEDURE
        the analysis.
                                                               3.3.1 PREPARATION OF

        3.2 AIM AND OBJECTIVES                                 SIMULATED SAMPLE


        3.2.1 AIM                                              1.  Flowerpot (firecracker) was taken and

        1.  To assess the reactivity of gunshot res-               lit  using  a  fire  source  (matchstick  or
           idue with Griess test and Walkers test :                lighter) to simulate the firearm’s con-
                                                                   fined barrel.
        i.  Analysis of samples collected  on                  2.  Wait for the cracker to burst and the

           gauze cloth.                                            residues are formed due to combustion
        ii. Analysis of samples at various inter-                  of the chemicals present in the cracker.
           vals of time after acquisition.                     3.  The  swab of the  simulated  GSR is
                                                                   taken  using a gauze  cloth  both from

        2.  To assess  the reactivity  of gunshot                  the surface and inside of the confined
           residue collected with different fabric                 space of the flowerpot.
           materials with Griess test and Walkers              4.  A negative  control sample is taken
           test.                                                   from the surface before bursting the
                                                                   cracker
                                                               5.  A positive control from an actual fire-

                                                                   arm is taken
                                                               6.  The samples are stored in a Petri dish
                                                                   and the analysis using Griess test and









                                                           40


                                                                                 Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[Walkers test takes place for samples at                 2.  It is soaked in a 0.5% solution of sul-
        different time intervals like                               phanilic  acid, dried, then swabbed

        a. ~ Fresh, 24 hours, 5 days, 10 days, 15                   with a 0.5% solution of Alpha-Naph-
        days, 30 days                                               thylamine in methyl alcohol, and again
        7. Freshly prepared sample of simulated                     dried.

           GSR is collected using different fabric              3.  A sheet of the prepared paper of suffi-
           materials like cotton gauze, jute and lin                cient size is placed with a thin dry cloth
           en.                                                      or towel or cotton cloth and the mate-
                                                                    rial to be tested is placed face down on
        3.3.2 PROCEDURE                                             the prepared paper.

                                                                4.  The whole preparation is then covered
        1. GRIESS TEST FOR NITRITES                                 with a thin dry cloth or towel slightly
                                                                    moistened with 20% solution of acetic

        1.  A drop of the neutral or acetic acid test               acid and then by another layer of dry
            solution is mixed on a spot plate with                  cloth.
            a drop each of sulfanilic acid and α–               5.  The entire pack is then pressed with a
            naphthylamine  solutions. According                     warm iron for several minutes.
            to the  nitrite  content, a  red colour  is

            formed either at once or after standing             3.3.4      UNDERSTANDING                  MUN-
            for a short time.                                   SELL’S COLOUR CHART THE
        2.  Reagents :                                          COLOUR  ATTRIBUTES

        i.  Solution of sulphanilic acid in acetic
            acid : 1 g sulphanilic acid is dissolved            1.  Hue is a colour, like red, green, or blue,
            by warming in 100 ml of 30% acetic                      for example. These are assigned letter
            acid.                                                   codes in the Munsell system, such as
        ii. Solution  of  α-naphthylamine-ace-                      Red (R), Yellow-Red (YR), Green (G),

            tic acid : 0.03 g α- naphthylamine is                   Green-Yellow (GY), and so on.
            boiled in 70 ml water; the colourless               2.  Value is a colour’ s lightness or dark-
            solution is decanted from the blue–vi-                  ness. Value is denoted by a number in

            olet residue and mixed with 30 ml gla-                  the Munsell system, such as 2, 4, 6,
            cial acetic acid.                                       and so on. A 2 will be darker than a 6
                                                                    because the value scale runs vertically
        2. WALKERS TEST FOR NITRITE                                 and goes from lightest (at the top) to

                                                                    darkest (at the bottom) in descending
        1.  Glossy  photographic  paper  is  fixed                  order.
            thoroughly in hypo solution to remove               3.  Chroma is how weak or strong a co-
            all the salts and then washed and dried.                lour is. In the Munsell system, Chroma









                                                           41

      Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[is indicated with a number, typically in the            3.  Keep GSR particles  away from  your
       range of 2-14 (upwards of 30 for colours                    skin. To avoid contamination and skin
       in  the  fluorescent  family).  The  Chroma                 exposure, always use gloves.
       scale runs horizontally and moves from                  4.  Maintain an organised and clean

       weak  (from the  left)  to  strong (to  the                 workspace to reduce the danger of-
       right), in ascending order, so a 2 is going                 cross-contamination.  Decontaminate
       to be weaker than a 6.                                      and disinfect surfaces and tools used
                                                                   for GSR testing on a regular basis.
                                                               5.  To reduce the danger of infection, use
                                                                   disposable items whenever possible.

                                                                   This covers swabs, filters, containers,
                                                                   and disposable gloves.
                                                               6.  When handling GSR samples, take

                                                                   care to prevent any needless agitation
                                    Fig 3.1 Hue                    or particle dispersion. Use careful han-
                                                                   dling techniques to reduce the produc-
                                                                   tion of aerosols or dust.
                                                               7.  Keep GSR samples in the proper con-


                                   Fig 3.2 Value                   tainers that are securely and legibly la-
                                                                   belled. This lessens the chance of con-
                                                                   fusion or unintentional exposure.

                                 Fig 3.3 Chroma                8.  Dispose of GSR-contaminated  items
                                                                   in accordance with regional laws and
                                                                   regulations.  Use the  authorised  trash

       PRECAUTIONS                                                 cans and adhere to the correct disposal
                                                                   procedures.

       1.  Wear the proper personal protective                 9.  Ensure that everyone handling or test-
           equipment  (PPE) to shield yourself                     ing GSR has received the necessary

           from any risks. Gloves, a lab coat or                   training. Keep current with the most
           other protective  equipment, safety                     recent GSR analysis best practices and
           glasses or goggles, and, if required, a                 guidelines.
           facemask are usually included in this.              10.  Perform a risk analysis prior to be-

       2.  To avoid breathing in potentially harm-                 ginning  a GSR analysis. Develop an
           ful vapours or particles, carry out GSR                 emergency response strategy for acci-
           handling and testing in a well-ventilat-                dents or spills, identify potential haz-
           ed location or within a fume hood.                      ards, and put appropriate controls in
                                                                   place.









                                                           42

                                                                                 Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[CHAPTER – IV                                            of Griess and Walkers test with the GSR

                                                                sample that was collected from the sur-
        4. OBSERVATIONS AND ANALYSIS                            face where control negative shows nega-
                                                                tive result and control positive shows pos-

        Table 4.1: Observation of Griess and Walkers test       itive result and rest of the samples tested
        from surface                                            show positive results as Gunshot Residue
                                                                were present.


                                                                Table 4.3: Observation of Griess and Walkers test
                                                                on different fabric materials












        The above table shows the reaction result
        of griess and walkers test with the GSR
        sample that was collected from the sur-

        face where control negative shows nega-                 The above table shows the reaction result
        tive result and control positive shows pos-             of griess and Walkers test with the GSR
        itive result and rest of the samples tested             sample  that  was  collected  on  different

        show positive results as Gunshot Residue                fabric materials where the control nega-
        were present.                                           tive samples shows negative for GSR and
                                                                for the freshly collected samples it shows

                                                                positive result due to the presence of GSR
        Table 4.2: Observation of Griess and Walkers test
        from the barrel                                         in them.

                                                                Table 4.4: Munsell’s colour chart readings for Griess
                                                                test for GSR samples from the barrel and the surface

















        The above table shows the reaction result









                                                           43

        Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[The above table shows the colour gradi-
       ent values of the reaction from the mun-                The above table shows the colour gradi-
       sell’s colour chart where it is seen that the           ent values of the reaction from the mun-
       difference between the sample collected                 sell’s colour chart where it is seen that the

       from the barrel and the surface is minimal              difference between the sample collected
       for griess test. The colour gradient values             from the barrel and the surface is large.
       are stronger in the less aged samples than              The colour gradient values are stronger in
       the other is.  The value for the 30 days                the less aged samples than the other is.

       goes high due to an excess of sample.
                                                               Table 4.7: Munsell’s colour chart readings for Walk-

       Table 4.5: Munsell’s colour chart readings for Griess   ers test on different fabric material
       test on different fabric material















                                                               The above table shows that cotton gauze

       The above table shows that cotton gauze                 is more reactive than with jute and jute
       is more reactive than with jute and jute                is more reactive than linen when samples
       is more reactive than linen when samples                are collected using these fabric materials.
       are collected using these fabric materials.
                                                               4.2 OBSERVATION IMAGES

       Table 4.6: Munsell’s colour chart readings for Walk-

       ers test for GSR samples from the barrel and the        4.2.1 GRIESS  TEST FOR RESIDUE
       surface                                                 ON GAUZE


















                                                               Figure 4.1: Standard sample reacting with the Griess
                                                               test






                                                           44

                                                                               Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[Figure 4.6: Sample tested after 15 days of collection
                                                                  from the barrel reacting with Griess test
        Figure 4.2: Freshly collected sample from the barrel
        reacting with the Griess test












                                                                  Figure 4.7: Sample tested after 30 days of collection
                                                                  from the barrel reacting with Griess test
        Figure 4.3: Sample tested after 24 hours of collec-

        tion from the barrel reacting with Griess test            4.2.2 GRIESS  TEST FOR RESIDUE
                                                                  FROM SURFACE

















        Figure 4.4: Sample tested after 5 days of collection      Figure 4.8: Freshly collected sample from the sur-
        from the barrel reacting with Griess test                 face reacting with the Griess test
















        Figure 4.5: Sample tested after 10 days of collection     Figure 4.9: Sample tested after 24 hours of collec-
        from the barrel reacting with Griess test                 tion from the surface reacting with Griess test









                                                           45

        Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[4.2.3 GRIESS  TEST FOR RESIDUE
                                                               ON DIFFERENT FABRIC

                                                               MATERIAL









       Figure 4.10: Sample tested after 5 days of collection

       from the surface reacting with Griess test







                                                               Figure 4.14: Freshly collected sample on cotton
                                                               gauze reacting with the Griess test







       Figure 4.11: Sample tested after 10 days of collec-
       tion from the surface reacting with Griess test







                                                               Figure 4.15: Freshly collected sample on Jute react-
                                                               ing with the Griess test





       Figure 4.12: Sample tested after 15 days of collec-

       tion from the surface reacting with Griess test













                                                               Figure 4.16: Freshly collected sample on Linen re-

       Figure 4.13: Sample tested after 30 days of collec-     acting with the Griess test
       tion from the surface reacting with Griess test







                                                             46


                                                                               Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[4.2.4 WALKERS TEST  FOR  RESI-
        DUE ON GAUZE














                                                                Figure 4.21: Sample tested after 10 days of collec-
        Figure 4.17: Standard sample reacting  with the         tion from the barrel reacting with Walkers test

        Walkers test













                                                                Figure 4.22: Sample tested after 15 days of collec-
                                                                tion from the barrel reacting with Walkers test
        Figure 4.18: Freshly collected sample from the bar-
        rel reacting with the Walkers test













                                                                Figure 4.23: Sample tested after 30 days of collec-
                                                                tion from the barrel reacting with Walkers test
        Figure 4.19: Sample tested after 24 hours of collec-
        tion from the barrel reacting with Walkers test         4.2.5 WALKERS TEST  FOR  RESI-
                                                                DUE FROM SURFACE












        Figure 4.20: Sample tested after 5 days of collection   Figure 4.24: Freshly collected sample from the sur-
        from the barrel reacting with Walkers test              face reacting with Walkers test









                                                           47

      Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[Figure 4.25: Sample tested after 24 hours of collec-    Figure 4.29: Sample tested after 30 days of collec-

       tion from the surface reacting with Walkers test        tion from the surface reacting with Walkers test


                                                               4.2.6 WALKERS TEST  FOR  RESI-
                                                               DUE ON DIFFERENT FABRIC
                                                               MATERIAL





       Figure 4.26: Sample tested after 5 days of collection

       from the surface reacting with Walkers test





                                                               Figure 4.30: Freshly collected sample on cotton
                                                               gauze reacting with Walkers test









       Figure 4.27: Sample tested after 10 days of collec-
       tion from the surface reacting with Walkers test

                                                               Figure 4.31: Freshly collected sample on jute react-
                                                               ing with Walkers test











       Figure 4.28: Sample tested after 15 days of collec-

       tion from the surface reacting with Walkers test        Figure 4.32: Freshly collected sample on linen re-
                                                               acting with Walkers test








                                                           48

                                                                                  Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[CHAPTER – V                                                aged sample whereas the sample from
                                                                   the chamber gave decent results.

        5. RESULTS AND DISCUSSIONS                            6.  When tested for nitrite residues on dif-
                                                                 ferent fabric material it is seen that the
        1.  the GSR samples. As per the observa-                 Griess test  shows better  results than

            tions, it is seen that the Griess test is            the Walkers test and it is seen that the
            more effective and sensitive than the                reactivity of GSR with the test is bet-
            Walkers test with the GSR.                           ter in cotton than jute and better in jute
        2.  The sample collected using gauze cloth               than linen (cotton>jute>linen)
            from the surface is slightly less sensi-          7.  Griess’ test is more sensitive than the

            tive  with  the  Griess test  when  com-             walkers  test  as per  the  observations
            pared with that of the sample collected              made even after the samples are old
            from inside the barrel (chamber of the               and aged.

            firecracker) which is highly sensitive            8.  The  colour concentrations  are  mea-
            even after the sample has aged.                      sured using Munsell’s colour chart to
        3.  The sample collected using gauze                     provide results that are more accurate
            cloth from the surface is least reactive             in a scientific manner.
            with the Walkers test when compared               9.  Griess’ test is more sensitive than the

            with that of the sample collected from               Walkers test and it is better to use Griess
            inside the barrel (chamber of the fire-              test for spot tests to identify the pres-
            cracker) which is sensitive even after               ence of GSR. We can see that there are

            the sample has aged.                                 many methods like SEM, SEM/EDX,
        4.  The sample tested at different intervals             Spectroscopy, Spectrophotometry and
            of time showed good sensitivity with                 many other chemical techniques which
            the Griess test, the colour concentra-               are time consuming and expensive.To
            tion drop is very minute in the Griess               identify  the  shooter  immediately  we

            test and gives better results for an aged            cannot wait for the results from the
            sample for both samples collected from               instrumental  techniques,  by the  time
            the surface and from the chamber.                    the results are obtained the perpetra-

        5.  The sample tested at different intervals             tor might try to escape. Whereas the
            of  time  showed  a  decent  sensitivity             Griess test is less time consuming and
            with the Walkers test, the colour con-               more  reactive  with  the  samples  that
            centration drop is enormous between                  are new and old as well. For example,
            different  timelines  when  the  samples             take Walker’s test that requires heat-

            were tested, the sample from the sur-                ing, which is not a feasible step when
            face showed the highest variation  in                the sample must be analysed in a scene
            the concentration of the colour for an               of crime, it requires









                                                           49

      Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[additional equipment ment to be carried,                than  the Walkers  test  when it  comes  to
       and it requires drying of the chemical                  identifying the nitrite residues in the GSR
       components used one after the other and                 sample, which gives the best sensitivity
       then the sample is tested. Griess test is a             when both the tests are compared.

       very simple and conventional method to
       use on the spot and the results are mostly              LIMITATIONS
       instantaneous.
                                                               The samples analysed for the nitrite res-

       CHAPTER – VI                                            idues are not the actual GSR that is pro-
                                                               duced by ammunition of a firearm. The
       6. CONCLUSIONS                                          sample obtained in the crime scene can be
       The Griess test has shown better reactivi-              very minute and the results can vary from

       ty with the samples than the Walkers test               the simulated sample used in this study.
       and the aged samples give better results                The samples used for analysis are in good
       with the Griess test. The Griess test helps             quantity for the reaction to occur where-
       save time and conduct more tests when                   as the actual samples from the scene of

       compared with the walkers test, which is                crime can be in trace amounts. The test
       a time consuming process and the reac-                  conducted  in  this study is only  for the
       tivity of the test with the samples is lesser           samples that are aged until 30 days but in
       when compared with the Griess test. The                 the actual crime investigation, the age of

       analysis and comparison started with the                the sample can be more than 30 days.
       freshly collected samples which are high-
       ly sensitive where the GSR was simulat-                 FUTURE PROSPECTS
       ed with the help of the flower pot which

       is a firecracker and swabbed with cotton                The Gunshot residue (GSR) can be test-
       gauze and other fabric materials like jute              ed using other methods such as Scanning
       and cotton, later tested for the presence of            Electron  Microscopy with Energy Dis-
       nitrite with the help of Griess and Walkers             persive X-ray Spectroscopy (SEM-EDS),

       test where the Griess test was superior to              Atomic Absorption Spectroscopy (AAS)
       the Walkers test. As the samples aged, the              and  Inductively  Coupled  Plasma-Mass
       reactivity of the sample with the Walkers               Spectrometry (ICP-MS),  Infrared Spec-
       test reduced whereas the Griess test was                troscopy that are the instrumentation tech-

       still effective and highly sensitive for the            niques,  which  can  give  accurate  results
       samples that were collected from the sur-               along with the details like composition of
       face as well as from the inside the cham-               the GSR, concentration of the GSR and
       ber of the cracker. Therefore, the Griess               many such details.  The usage of actual

       test is recommended as the better practice              GSR will give more accurate results than








                                                           50

                                                                                 Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[the simulated GSR and the test will have                   April 8). The analysis of organic and
        results that can be seen in real life scenar-              inorganic GSR from a single sample.
        ios. The time durations can be increased                   Forensic Science International. https://

        to check the reactivity of the Griess and                  doi.org/10.1016/j.forsciint.2019.03.049
        Walkers test with the GSR collected on                 6.  Goudsmits, e.,  &  Sharples,  g. p.
        different materials, as it would show the                  (2015). Recent trends in organic gun-
        maximum  GSR containing capacity  of                       shot residue analysis. Trends in analyt-

        the fabric materials  and reveal the test                  ical chemistry.
        that is suitable.                                      7.  Hallett j. (2019). Examination of gun-
                                                                   shot residue arising from shotgun car-
        CHAPTER – VII                                              tridges containing steel, bismuth or
                                                                   tungsten pellets. Forensic Science In-

        7. REFERENCES                                              ternational. : https://doi.org/10.1016/j.
                                                                   forsciint.2019.110096
        1.  Abdul Halim, M. i., & Ahmad, u. k.                 8.  Heringer, r. d., & Ranville, j. f. (2018,

            (2010, December).  Analysis of GSR                     may 25). GSR analysis by single par-
            deposited on cloth target. International               ticle inductively coupled plasma mass
            Conference on Science and Social Re-                   spectrometry. Forensic Science In-
            search.                                                ternational.  https://doi.org/10.1016/j.

        2.  Arouca, a. m., & Lucena,  M. a.m.                      forsciint.2018.05.010
            (2019).  Analysis  of Luminescent                  9.  kersh, k. l., & Childers, j. m. (2014,
            Gunshot  Residue  (LGSR)  on  Differ-                  may).  Detection  of gunshot residue
            ent  Types of Fabrics. Journal  of Fo-                 on dark coloured  clothing  prior  to

            rensic Science. doi: 10.1111/1556-                     chemical  analysis. Journal  of Foren-
            4029.14143                                             sic Science, 59(3). doi: 10.1111/1556-
        3.  Butt, m., & Ghouri, m. s. (2016, De-                   4029.12409
            cember). Trace analysis of gunshot res-            10.  M.  Aliste L.G. Chavez. (2016).

            idue on different fabrics using locally                Analysis of gunshot residues as trac-
            manufactured ammunition in pakistan.                   es in nasal mucus by GFAAS. Fo-
            International  Journal  of  Scientific  &              rensic  Science  International.  DOI:
            Engineering Research, 7(12).                           http://dx.doi.org/doi:10.1016/j.forsci-

        4.  Charles, s., & Lannoy, m. (2013, March                 int.2016.01.034
            16). Influence of type of fabric on the            11.  Mishra, r. k., & Budania, a. (2022).
            collection efficiency of GSR. Forensic                 Case report:a pilot study on review of
            Science  International.  http://dx.doi.                gunshot residue with a case study. In-

            org/10.1016/j.forsciint.2013.02.022                    dian Journal of Forensic and Commu-
        5.  Goudsmits, e., & Blakey, l. s. (2019,                  nity Medicine, 9(3), 139-145. https://
                                                                   doi.org/10.18231/j.ijfcm.2022.030







                                                           51


      Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[doi.org/10.18231/j.ijfcm.2022.030                           Contemporary   Security   Manage
        12.  Rafae, a. a. m., & Ali, s. f. m. (2019).               ment. Butterworth-Heinemann.
            Colorimetric based detection of GSR                20.  Bailey, J. A., Casanova, R. S., &

            on gloves worn during shooting. Ma-                    Bufkin, K. (2006). A method for en-
            laysian Journal of Analytical Sciences,                hancing gunshot residue patterns on
            23(2), 229-236.                                        dark and multicoloured fabrics com-
        13.  R Rajaramakrishna, & kaewkhao,                        pared  with  the  modified  Griess  test.

            j. (n.d.). Glass material and their ad-                Journal of forensic  sciences,  51(4),
            vanced  applications.  KnE social  sci-                812-814.
            ences, 2019. 10.18502/kss.v3i18.4769               21.  Berendes, A., Neimke, D., Schum-
        14.  Shrivastava, p., & v.k. (2011). Gun-                  acher, R., & Barth, M. (2006). A ver-

            shot residue  detection technologies-a                 satile  technique  for the  investigation
            review. Egyptian Journal of Forensic                   of gunshot residue patterns on fabrics
            Sciences.                                              and other surfaces: m‐ XRF. Journal of
        15.  Seyfang, k. E., Lucas, n., & Red-                     forensic sciences, 51(5), 1085-1090.

            man, k. E. (2019, March 14). Glass                 22.  Kersh, K. L., Childers, J. M., Jus-
            containing  gunshot residues and par-                  tice, D., & Karim, G. (2014). Detection
            ticles of industrial and occupational                  of  gunshot  residue  on  dark‐coloured
            origins:considerations  for evaluating                 clothing  prior to  chemical  analysis.

            GSR traces. Forensic Science Interna-                  Journal of forensic  sciences,  59(3),
            tional.                                                754-762.
        16.  Silvia, f., & Profumo, a. (2020,                  23.  Brożek-Mucha,  Z.  (2017).  Trends
            December).  Interaction of GSR with                    in analysis of gunshot residue for fo-

            natural  and synthetic  textiles  hav-                 rensic purposes. Analytical and bioan-
            ing  different  structural  features.  El-             alytical chemistry, 409, 5803-5811.
            sevier, 2. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.              24.  O’Mahony,  A. M., &  Wang, J.
            talo.2020.100017                                       (2013).  Electrochemical  detection  of

        17.  Siti Nurhazlin  Jaluddin, & Zain-                     gunshot residue for forensic analysis:
            iharyati  Mohd Zain. (2021, October                    a review. Electroanalysis, 25(6), 1341-
            26).  Preliminary  Evaluation  of  Gun-                1358.
            shot Residue (GSR)  Using  3-Amin-

            ophenol  as  a  Substitute  in  Modified
            Griess Test. Research gate. 10.22146/
            ijc.68265                                            Alfymol Anto Narithookkil,
        18.  Crime Scene Investigator Network.

            (n.d.)                                               Joshua Stephen,
        19.  Patterson, D.,   &   Fay,   J.   (2017).            Riya Thomas,
                                                                 Devi S







                                                           52


                                                                                 Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[IMPACT OF FAMILY FACTOR




           LEADING TO CRIMINAL



           BEHAVIOUR IN ADULTHOOD






             ABSTRACT:
                                                                 Key words: Family environment, Pa-
             The goal of the current study was to                rental  up-bringing, socio-economic

             identify family characteristics that af-            status.
             fected men and women’s behaviour in
             social settings, including whether they             INTRODUCTION
             became lawbreakers or showed signs

             of becoming socially responsible. The               Cognitive  theory of psychology fo-
             self-reporting format of the prepared               cuses on how human thinking pro-
             questionnaire  was used to  conduct                 cesses can affect a certain person’s life
             this comparison study. 50 samples                   in a given situation. Family is the first

             made up the study’s subject, out of                 place where we learn about all the val-
             which 15 were female and 35 were                    ues as well the kind of behaviour we
             male.  Crime-committing individuals                 must replicate in the society in order
             believed their parents to have higher               to survive in the outside world. Also

             levels of dysfunctional parent-partner              by the social learning theory of Albert
             interactions, poor family functioning,              Bandura, it is mentioned that a grow-
             and higher levels of family violence                ing kid will learn and pursue things as
             than socially organised persons. Addi-              they are thought by their parents and

             tionally, criminals were found to have              every individual as a kid will grow up
             higher rates of psychosomatic symp-                 under the supervision of their parents
             toms, antisocial personality traits, and            and family members, so the kid here
             frustration,  hatred,  anger, and other             tries to follow and pursue things as

             strong emotions that were interpret-                their parents do and teach them. (Mc-
             ed negatively and led to criminal be-               leod, 2023)
             haviour. In contrast, anyone who had                Cohesiveness of family is defined as
             grown up in a social setting and faced              the emotional bonding of the family

             similar circumstances still emerged as              members  towards each other.  While
             a social being when they approached                 this cohesiveness of the family is also,
             it as a challenge and came to a posi-
             tive conclusion.


                                                           53


     Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[considered as the most effective factor for             all interact to shape an individual’s devel-
 IMPACT OF FAMILY FACTOR   protection against the external stressors.   opment  and subsequent  engagement  in

                                                               criminal  activities. Understanding these

 LEADING TO CRIMINAL   Economic condition of the family impacts   factors  is  crucial  in  designing  effective
                                                               prevention  and intervention  strategies
       the family in both positive and negative
 BEHAVIOUR IN ADULTHOOD  altitudes.  In a  nuclear  family, pressures   that promote positive parenting practices,
                                                               provide support to at-risk families,  and
       like unemployment, foreclosure, or loss
       put a strain on the ties between the par-               address the root causes of criminal  be-

       ents and the family as a whole. (Dicke et               haviour. By fostering healthy family en-
       al., 2018)                                              vironments, we can contribute to the re-
                                                               duction of criminality and create a more
       If a family’s basic  necessities,  such as              supportive and inclusive society. (Fergus-

       access to food security, healthcare,  and               son et al., 2019)
       housing, are not met, their position may
       be much more dire.  When basic condi-                   METHODOLOGY:
       tions are improper and the kids who de-

       velop in this kind of socio-economic con-               Aim:
       dition will tend to develop deviation from              To determine  the impact of family fac-
       the society. There are researches to prove              tors, leading to  criminal  behaviour, in
       that  worsening in the economy  can  led                adulthood.

       to impact the raise in the family conflict,
       child neglect and child abuse also the in-              Objectives:
       mate partner violence. (Dicke et al., 2018)             1.  To study the socio economic  factors
       Research  consistently  demonstrates  that                  inducing criminal behaviour in adult-

       parental  factors  play  a  critical  role  in              hood
       shaping an individual’s behaviour  and                  2.  To  find  the  most  affecting  and  least
       can contribute to the risk of criminality                   affecting social and economic factors
       in adulthood. Parental factors encompass                    contributing to criminal behaviour.

       a range of dimensions, including parent-                3.  To study the percentage of the subjects
       ing styles, parental  involvement,  family                  that fall for criminality due to family
       dynamics, parental criminality, and the                     factors .
       presence of abuse or neglect  within the                4.  To study and understand family situa-

       family. (Fergusson et al., 2019)                            tional factors which impact on the per-
                                                                   son’s life leading them to criminal and
       Parenting  styles, parental  involvement,                   hence to provide preventive steps and
       the presence of abuse or neglect, parental                  rehabilitation

       criminality, and socioeconomic status








                                                           54


                                                                                 Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="64"><![CDATA[SAMPLE COLLECTION                                      SAMPLE SIZE



        A standard questionnaire was formulated                The  subject  consisted of a  total  of 50
        with the help of guides and psychologists              samples of which 35 male convicted in-

        by referring to a standard set of protocols            mates  and  15 female  convicted  inmates
        that must be followed. The questionnaire               serving their punishment at prison were
        consists of 90 standard simple yes or no               considered. Sampling was done using
        questions  related to  family environment              convenience  sampling technique.  None
        and family situation. A consent form was               were given parole as per records and had

        firstly taken pertaining to the confidenti-            minimum  connection with the family
        ality of the agreement for the sample col-             environment  after their conviction.  The
        lection including age, sex, parental back-             conviction period of the convicted was in

        ground, education and so on.. The consent              between 6 months to 20 years of the sub-
        form was taken with a signature or thumb               ject samples obtained.
        impression from the subject.
                                                               Process of collection of samples
        Intrusion factor includes

        •  The criminals from heinous crime such               1.  The rapport was established with the
            as murder, rape etc                                    subject.
        •  The convicted inmates from the prison               2.  The questionnaire sheet was provided

        •  The inmates with no psychological is-                   to the subject.
            sues                                               3.  The instruction was given to the sub-
        •  Both literates  and illiterates  of same                ject priorly; as to read the question and
            kind                                                   answer them accordingly (for liter-
        •  Only socio economic factors such as                     ates).

            occupation, family, income play a ma-              4.  The questionnaire should be read out
            jor role.                                              to  the  subject  carefully  and  the  an-
                                                                   swers must  be  recorded  accordingly

        Extrusion factors includes                                 (for illiterates).
        •  The inmates who are not convicted.                  5.  Right tick on the correct answer with
        •  The inmates who are from a non hei-                     the help of a pencil was considered.
            nous crime background.                             6.  The first thought in mind for the an-
        •  The inmates with psychological issues.                  swer was collected in the format of yes

        •  The inmates are in custody.                             or no.
        •  The inmate’s age group is not a crite-              7.  The time limit of 20 - 30 minutes was
            ria.                                                   provided.











                                                           55

        Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="65"><![CDATA[Table 4.3: showing education of the subject.
       Table 4.1:  Showing subject’s Age.



















                                                               Table 4.3 provides information about the
                                                               education levels of a group of subjects.


       The table 4.1 provides information on the               According to the table, there is a total of
       age distribution of convicted criminals in              50 of subjects considered.
       a specific dataset. Out of the population
       chosen for this study, 46% of respondents               Table 4.4: Showing subject’s Occupation.

       are between the ages of 20 and 29. which                .
       amounts to 23 individuals out of the total
       population of 50 individuals.



       Table 4.2:  Showing gender of the individuals.










                                                               The table 4.4 provides information on the
                                                               occupation of the convicted criminals in

                                                               a specific dataset. Out of the population

       Table 4.2 provides information about in-                chosen for the study 40% of respondents
       dividuals convicted, categorised by gen-                fall in the category farmer, which amounts
       der. The total population of this study in-             to 20 individuals out of the total popula-

       cludes 50 individuals convicted.                        tion of 50 individuals.

















                                                           56

                                                                               Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="66"><![CDATA[Table 4.5: Showing subject’s income.                   Table 4.8: Showing Parental education of subjects





















                                                               Table 4.9:  the subject’s parental occupation



        The table 4.5 provides information about
        the income of the convicted criminals in
        the specific data table



        Table 4.6: Showing subject’s Type of family









                                                               Table 4.9 provided information about the parental
                                                               occupation of the  convicted  subjects .





        The table 4.6, provides information on the
        type of family of the convicted criminals
        in a specific dataset.



        Table 4.7: Showing Parenting of subjects
























                                                           57

      Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="67"><![CDATA[Table 4.10:  Showing subject’s Parental income.         determine how much of a family’s influ-
                                                               ence on a person’s decision to commit a
                                                               crime. The result of this study provides

                                                               preventive steps and rehabilitation of the
                                                               individuals who fall for criminality due to
                                                               family factors.










       The table  4.10 provides information  on
       the parental income of the convicted
       criminals in a specific dataset.



       Table 4.11: Showing subject’s crime type                The above pie chart explains the amount
                                                               of  effect  caused  because  of  a  family’s
                                                               socio-economic  factors like poverty,
                                                               education,  occupation, type of fami-
                                                               ly, and parenting type being responsible

                                                               for criminality.  The subject’s response
                                                               showed that more than 97.7% of the data
                                                               sampling believed that due to impairment

                                                               in their familial situation as explained in
                                                               the tables in the above analysis, are the
                                                               factors responsible for turning them into

       Result:                                                 criminals.


       Influence of social character in the sense              DISCUSSION:
       of relationship within the family includ-

       ing parental  relationship, relationship                In the analysis, socioeconomic disparities
       with siblings, neighbours, relatives,  are              and  social  inequality contribute  to  feel-
       the major factor in the people’s behaviour,             ings of marginalisation and exclusion,
       giving out the largest difference in the so-            which can foster criminal  behaviour.

       ciety  as social  people and criminals.  In             When individuals perceive unfairness or
       conclusion, it is found that family is an               a lack of opportunities for upward mobil-
       affecting factor as explained in the anal-              ity, they may resort to illegal means to ex-
       ysis. However, the goal of this study is to             press their frustrations or seek a sense of
                                                               empowerment.







                                                           58

                                                                                 Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="68"><![CDATA[Additionally, social exclusion can lead to              criminal  networks and a higher  preva-
        social  disorganisation  within communi-                lence of criminal behaviour.
        ties, weakening social bonds and increas-

        ing the prevalence of criminal activities.              Education  and employment  play crucial
                                                                roles in shaping an individual’s socio-
        Parenting style and family dysfunction                  economic  status and their  susceptibility
        significantly  influence  a  child’s  sociali-          to criminal behaviour. Limited access to

        sation and moral  development.  Author-                 quality  education  and job opportunities
        itarian  or neglectful parenting styles,                can  hinder social  mobility  and increase
        characterised by lack of warmth, incon-                 the likelihood of engaging in criminal
        sistent discipline, or excessive control,               activities.  Without  adequate  education,

        have been linked to an increased risk of                individuals  may  struggle  to  find  stable
        criminal behaviour in children. Similarly,              employment,  leading to economic  inse-
        dysfunctional  family  dynamics  such as                curity and potential involvement in ille-
        violence, substance abuse, or neglect can               gal activities as an alternative source of

        contribute to the development of criminal               income. Furthermore, unemployment and
        tendencies in individuals. Children grow-               underemployment can create frustration,
        ing  up  in  such environments  may  lack               resentment, and a sense of hopelessness,
        positive role models, experience a lack of              which may increase the risk of criminal

        emotional support, and internalise nega-                behaviour.
        tive behaviours and values.
                                                                CONCLUSION:
        One of the most significant socioeconom-

        ic  factors  associated  with  criminality  is          In conclusion,  the impact  of the  family
        poverty. Numerous  studies  have  consis-               factor on leading to criminal behaviour in
        tently found a correlation between pov-                 adulthood is undeniable. Research con-
        erty and crime rates. Poverty creates an                sistently  shows that  a dysfunctional  or

        environment characterised by limited ac-                troubled  family  environment  increases
        cess to basic needs, inadequate education,              the risk of criminal  behaviour. Parental
        and limited employment  opportunities.                  influence, family structure, parental sub-
        These situations may push people to turn                stance abuse, socioeconomic factors, and

        to crime as a method of surviving or as                 the presence of protective factors all play
        a way to better their financial status. Ad-             a role in shaping an individual’s propen-
        ditionally, the lack of social support and              sity for criminal activity.
        resources in impoverished communities

        may contribute to the formation of                      The behaviour and actions of parents sig-
                                                                nificantly influence the development









                                                           59


    Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="69"><![CDATA[of children, and parental neglect, abuse,               criminal behaviour in adulthood and fos-
       or inconsistent discipline can increase                 tering healthier and safer communities.
       the  likelihood of criminal  behaviour  in

       adulthood. Family structure, such as sin-               REFERENCES
       gle-parent  households or high  levels  of
       conflict,  can  contribute  to  an  increased           1.  Bhandari, A. (2018, april). The Role
       risk. Parental substance abuse, particular-                 of the Family in Crime Causation: A

       ly when exposed to children, has a strong                   Comparative Study of ‘Family of Ori-
       association with an increased risk of crim-                 entation  family of Orientation’ and
       inal behaviour.                                             ‘F ’ and ‘Family of Pr family of Pro-
                                                                   creation’ (A Study of ’ (A Study of

       Socioeconomic  factors also come into                       Women Prisoners in the Central Jails
       play, as low-income families  often face                    of Rajasthan). Journal of Internation-
       greater challenges and have limited  ac-                    al  Women’s  Studies, 19(3), 109-118.
       cess to resources, education, and employ-                   https://vc.bridgew.edu/cgi/viewcon-

       ment opportunities. These circumstances                     tent.cgi?article=2028&context=jiws
       can  increase  the  likelihood  of criminal             2.  Bharadwaj, & Ashish. (2014). .Is pov-
       involvement.  However, the  presence  of                    erty  the  mother  of  crime?  Empirical
       protective factors, such as supportive re-                  evidence  of the  impact  of socioeco-

       lationships, positive peer influences, ac-                  nomic factors on crime in India. Atlan-
       cess to education  and employment  op-                      tic Review of Economics, 1.http://hdl.
       portunities, and community involvement,                     handle.net/10419/146581
       can mitigate these risks and promote pos-               3.  Fajnzylber, P, Loayza,  N, & Leder-

       itive outcomes.                                             man, D. (2002). What causes violent
                                                                   crime?  European economic  review,
       To address the impact of the family fac-                    46(7), 1323-1357. https://www.sci-
       tor on criminal behaviour, it is essential                  encedirect.com/science/article/pii/

       to implement  preventive  measures  and                     S0014292101000964
       intervention  strategies that consider the              4.  Fergusson, D. M., Boden, J. M., &
       multifaceted nature of the issue. This may                  Horwood, L. J. (2019, May 7). .Den-
       involve providing support and resources                     tine lead levels in childhood and crim-

       to families, promoting positive parenting                   inal behaviour in late adolescence and
       practices, addressing substance abuse is-                   early adulthood. Journal of Epidemi-
       sues, and improving access to education                     ology & Community Health 2008. Re-
       and employment opportunities.  By ad-                       trieved May 2, 2023, from https://jech.

       dressing these  factors comprehensively,                    bmj.com/content/62/12/1045.info
       we can work towards reducing the risk of                5.  Friedman, S. D. (2018, November 14).









                                                           60


                                                                               Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="70"><![CDATA[review of management and busi-
            How Our Careers Affect Our Children.                         ness research, 2(1). https://www.re-
        qsHarvard Business Review. Retrieved                    searchgate.net/profile/David-Ishor/

           May 4, 2023, from https://hbr                        publicaion/358432213_African_Cul-
           org/2018/11/how-our-careers-affect-                  tural_Practices_and_Health_Implica-
           our-children                                         tions_for_Nigeria_Rural_Development/
        6.  Ghiasi N, Azhar Y, Singh J. Psychiat-               links/620277154d89183b338cddf1/Af-
            ric Illness And Criminality. [Updated               rican-Cultural-Practices-and-Health-Im-

            2023 Jan 9]. In: StatPearls [Internet].             plications-for-Nigeria-Rural-Deve
            Treasure Island (FL): StatPearls Pub-               11.  Schwartz, S.  (2020, January 23).
            lishing;  2023 Jan-.  Available  from:                 How  a  Parent’s  Affection  Shapes  a

            https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/                    Child’s Happiness | SPSP. The Society
            NBK537064/                                             for Personality and Social Psychol-
        7.  Hay, C., Fortson, E. N.,  Hollist, D.                  ogy. Retrieved April 24, 2023, from
            R., Altheimer, I., &  Schaible,  L. M.                 https://spsp.org/news-center/charac-
            (2006).  The  Impact  of Community                     ter-context-blog/how-parents-affec-

            Disadvantage on the Relationship be-                   tion-shapes-childs-happiness
            tween the Family and Juvenile Crime.                12.  Stattin,  H., & Magnusson, D.
            Journal of Research in Crime and De-                   (1989).  The  role  of early  aggressive

            linquency, 43(4), 326-356. https://doi.                behavior in the frequency, seriousness,
            org/10.1177/0022427806291262                           and type of later  crime. Journal of
        8.  McCORD, J. (1991, august).  Fam-                       Consulting and Clinical  Psychology,
            ily relationships, juvenile  delin-                    57(6), 710-718. https://psycnet.apa.
            quency, and adult criminality. Crim-                   org/doi/10.1037/0022-006X.57.6.71

            inology, 29(3), 397-417. https://                   13.  Tehrani, J. A., Brennan, P. A., Hod-
            doi.org/10.1111/j.1745-9125.1991.                      gans, S., & Mednick, S.  A. (1998).
            tb01072.                                               Mental illness and criminal violence.

        9.  Mcleod,  S. (2023, February  16). Al-                  socialpsychiatry  and psychiatric  epi-
            bert Bandura’s Social Learning Theo-                   demiology, (33), S81-S85.
            ry. Simply Psychology.https://simply-               14.  Thompson, K.  (2017, July 29).
            psychology.org/bandura.html                            Bandura, Ross and Ross (1961) – The
        10.  Ojua, T. A., Ishor, D., & Ndom, P.                    Imitative  Aggressive  Experiment.

            (2013, 3).  African  cultural  practices               ReviseSociology.Retrieved  April  1,
            and health implications for Nigeria ru-                2023,  from  https://revisesociology.
            ral development. International                         com/2017/07/29/bobo-doll-experi-

                                                                   ment/








                                                           61

      Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="71"><![CDATA[15.  Viemero, V. (1996). Factors in child-
             hood that predict later criminal behav-
             ior. aggressive behavior, 22(2), 87-97.

             https://doi.org/10.1002/(SICI)1098-
             -2337(1996)22:2%3C87::AID-
             AB2%3E3.0.CO;2-R











































                                                               Nisarga Lakshmi,

                                                               C N Manu Shree,

                                                               Sreelakshmi N M,

                                                               Pooja V,

                                                               Disha S N,

                                                               Don Caeiro
















                                                           62

                                                                                 Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="72"><![CDATA[GLOBAL NEWS UPDATE















                                      Nexus Between Tailored Access
                      1               N  e xus Bet      w   een T     a ilor  ed Access
                                      Operations And Digital Forensics
                                      Oper
                                                                                    or
                                                                               l F
                                                 tions And Digita
                                               a
                                                                                        ensics

                                     Cerumen – A Potential Source Of Help
                      2              Cer    umen – A P           otential Sour           ce Of Help
                                                      ion Of T
                                                                     o
                                                                       xins
                                                     t
                                     In Det
                                     In Detection Of Toxins
                                                 ec



                      3               Sma     r t W  at er
                                      SmartWater












































                                                         63

     Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="73"><![CDATA[NEXUS BETWEEN




         TAILORED ACCESS




         OPERATIONS AND




         DIGITAL FORENSICS







        INTRODUCTION                                         computer  systems, networks, and devices.
                                                             Driven by intelligence-gathering  objectives,

        As we move ahead in the revolutionary                TAO operatives  meticulously  craft  custom
        world of cybersecurity and intelligence,             exploits, develop intricate malware, and em-
        two prominent and interconnected  do-                ploy covert methodologies to breach security
        mains have emerged: tailored  access                 measures. These operations are executed with
        operations (TAO) and digital forensics.              the utmost precision, aiming to remain unde-

        These  fields,  though  distinct,  share  a          tected while extracting sensitive information
        complex  relationship as they navigate               for intelligence analysis.
        the intricate world of cyber operations,

        intrusion detection,  and information                THE DIGITAL FORENSICS
        analysis. This article delves into the nu-
        anced interplay between TAO and digital              In contrast to the covert manoeuvres of TAO,
        forensics, shedding light on their respec-           digital forensics is a transparent and system-
        tive roles, methodologies, and implica-              atic  process employed to investigate  cyber

        tions for the realm of cybersecurity.                incidents.  This discipline revolves around
                                                             collecting,  analysing,  and  preserving  digital

        THE TAILORED ACCESS OPERA-                           evidence originating from compromised sys-

        TIONS (TAO)                                          tems, networks, and electronic devices. Digi-
                                                             tal forensics experts painstakingly reconstruct

        Tailored Access Operations, often abbre-             the chronology of events, discern the extent
        viated as TAO, represents a clandestine              of breaches, and identify the perpetrators re-
        facet  of  cyber  espionage  orchestrated            sponsible. Through a meticulous examination

        by intelligence agencies. TAO’s modus                of system logs, network traffic, and file sys-
        operandi  involves deploying  advanced               tems, digital forensics serves as the investiga-
        hacking  techniques  to  infiltrate  target          tive backbone for unravelling the mysteries of
                                                             cyberattacks.



                                                           64



                                                                                 Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="74"><![CDATA[THE NEXUS: HOW TAO AND DIGI-                            ploy an array of specialised tools to re-
       TAL FORENSICS CONVERGE?                                 construct cyber incidents. These tools aid

                                                               in deciphering the intricacies of cyberat-
       While  TAO and digital  forensics might                 tacks and empower analysts to unravel
       seem  disparate,  they are  intertwined  in             the methods used by attackers.
       ways that  illuminate  the  intricate  facets
       of modern cybersecurity.                                ATTRIBUTION  AND  COUNTER-

                                                               MEASURES


       DATA  COLLECTION AND  ANALY-                            TAO:  Intelligence  agencies executing
       SIS                                                     TAO operations often seek to mask their

                                                               identity, employing deception and misdi-
       TAO: Tailored Access Operations thrives                 rection to deter attribution.
       on collecting sensitive information from
       compromised systems. The data extracted                 Forensics: Digital forensics plays a piv-

       is later funnelled to intelligence agencies             otal  role  in attribution  by meticulously
       for comprehensive analysis, shaping na-                 tracing  digital  footprints  and discerning
       tional security strategies.                             the  origin  of cyberattacks. This attribu-

                                                               tion is instrumental in devising effective
       Forensics:  Digital  forensics profession-              countermeasures and proactive strategies.
       als,  too, engage  in  data  collection  and
       analysis,  albeit  for  different  ends. Their          IMPLICATIONS AND  FUTURE  DI-
       efforts  focus  on  deciphering  the  tactics           RECTIONS

       and techniques employed by cybercrimi-
       nals, thereby contributing to the develop-              The convergence of TAO and digital fo-
       ment of robust defence mechanisms.                      rensics carries profound implications for

                                                               the  realm  of cybersecurity.  As intelli-
       TECHNIQUES AND TOOLS                                    gence agencies continue to harness TAO
                                                               for espionage and national  security, the
       TAO:  The  arsenal  of  TAO encompass-                  need for skilled digital forensics profes-
       es cutting-edge  hacking  techniques,  ze-              sionals becomes ever more critical. Ro-

       ro-day exploits, and meticulously  de-                  bust digital forensics capabilities enable
       signed malware. These tools enable TAO                  the detection, investigation, and mitiga-
       operatives  to  infiltrate  systems  with  re-          tion of cyber threats, thus fortifying cyber

       markable stealth and precision.                         defences on a global scale.


       Forensics: Digital forensics experts em                 Looking ahead, the synergy between






                                                           65


     Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="75"><![CDATA[TAO and digital forensics is poised to                REFERENCES
       evolve. Intelligence agencies may refine

       their TAO tactics in response to advances  1.  Peterson,  A. (2021,  December  6).
       in digital forensics, prompting a perpet-                The NSA has its team of elite  hack-
       ual cycle of innovation and adaptation.                  ers.  Washington Post. https://www.
       Moreover, the growing emphasis on                        washingtonpost.com/blogs/the-switch/
       international collaboration in cybersecu-                wp/2013/08/29/the-nsa-has-its-own-

       rity efforts underscores the importance                  team-of-elite-hackers/?tid=d_pulse
       of aligning TAO operations with ethical               2.  Kingsbury,  A. (2009, June 19).  The
       considerations and legal frameworks.                     Secret History of the National Securi-

                                                                ty Agency. US News & World Report.
       CONCLUSION                                               https://www.usnews.com/opinion/
                                                                articles/2009/06/19/the-secret-histo-
       In  the dynamic  landscape  of cybersecu-                ry-of-the-national-security-agency
       rity, the relationship between tailored ac-           3.  Hacking  Exposed Computer  Foren-

       cess operations and digital forensics is a               sics, second edition. (n.d.). Google
       testament  to the multifaceted  nature of                Books.         https://books.google.com/
       modern espionage and threat detection.                   books?id=yMdNrgSBUq0C

       While TAO operates in the shadows, dig-               4.  Wikipedia  contributors.  (n.d.). Book
       ital forensics brings these covert activities            sources -  Wikipedia.  https://en.wiki-
       to light through meticulous analysis and                 pedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSourc-
       investigation. This symbiotic relationship               es/978-0-07-162677-4
       underscores the importance of a compre-               5.  Wikipedia  contributors.  (2023a).  For

       hensive  and  holistic  approach  to  cyber-             dummies. Wikipedia.  https://en.wiki-
       security,  where  offensive  and  defensive              pedia.org/wiki/For_Dummies
       strategies  converge to safeguard digital  6.  Wikipedia contributors. (n.d.-b). Book

       landscapes in an interconnected world.                   sources -  Wikipedia.  https://en.wiki-
                                                                pedia.org/wiki/Special:BookSourc-
                                                                es/978-0-470-37191-6














                                                                               Debashis Das








                                                           66


                                                                               Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="76"><![CDATA[CERUMEN –




        A POTENTIAL SOURCE OF




        HELP IN DETECTION OF




                  TOXINS






        INTRODUCTION



        Worldwide we come across a lot of drug
        cases with urine, blood, nails and hair
        being analysed in the forensic labs, but

        these often have a lot of limitations to
        it.  Many of the drugs or toxins are not
        administered in the urine and blood due
        to its short half-life and also due to less
        convenient  collection  methods. Similar               Image 1: Depicting Biological Sample analysis

        is the case with the nails and hair, as they
        are part of external cartilage, they seem            cal analysis. Studies and researches were made
        to be more prone to damages or loss of               and CERUMEN- also called  as ear-wax was

        drug content due to various contaminants             found to be a good source to detect  toxins
        from the  external  environment.  So, in             which even persisted for a longer duration as
        such cases it may occur that by the time             compared to the other biological fluids.
        these biological samples are analysed it
        may lose all the potential clue pertaining            What exactly is cerumen?

        to the drug which was initially present
        and thus seem to prove useless.                      Cerumen also called as earwax is a naturally
                                                             occurring wax like substance present in the

        Until recently earwax was not given that             external  auditory canal which prevents the
        much of importance  and only viewed                  dust from entering inside the ear and also pro-
        as a waste or neglected body secretion.              vides lubrication. It is composed of epithelial
        Concerns were rising and there was a                 cells  and  certain  secretions  from  sebaceous
        quest regarding an alternative to a bio-             glands and modified apocrine sweat glands.

        logical fluid which can aid in toxicologi



                                                           67



    Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="77"><![CDATA[Why is it better to the other fluids?                 CONCLUSION


        It is exactly not considered better but due           CERUMEN being a good storage for

        to its durability for a longer time it cannot         toxins for a longer duration can be con-
        be neglected either.                                  sidered as an alternative for the detection
        As cerumen is secreted  from apocrine                 of toxins and drugs. The research thus be-
        sweat  glands, they  have  high  chanc-               ing successful showed the usefulness of

        es of transporting  any  drug molecules               earwax as a tool to detect drugs or toxins
        being administered  in the body via                   being present in the body which can fur-
        the sweat glands surrounding these                    ther aid in the investigation of cases re-
        ceruminous  glands. It could  aid  in                 lated to drug abuse, poisoning and case

        gaining information about an individual               of death to rule out any foul play.
        such as the ethnicity, the race, the food
        eaten and certain diseases. Also, as it is            REFERENCES
        not  exactly  in  contact  with  the  external

        environment it can be detected even after             1.  Shokry,  E.,  Marques,  J. G., Ragazzo,
        a few days as compared to urine or blood                  P. C., Pereira, N. Z., & Filho, N. R. A.
        which can wash off its presence.                          (2017). Earwax as an alternative spec-
                                                                  imen for forensic analysis. Forensic

                                                                  Toxicology, 35(2), 348–358.
        Research was made on this and 17 pa-
        tients were administered with 12 different            2.  https://doi.org/10.1007/s11419-017-
        types of drug whose molecules were later                  0363-z Cerumen impaction  - Symp-
        found to present in the earwax which was                  toms, diagnosis  and treatment  |  BMJ

        a major deciding point about its accuracy                 Best Practice US.  (n.d.). https://best-
        and feasibility.                                          practice.bmj.com/topics/en-us/1032
                                                              3.  Wikipedia  contributors. (2023). Ear-
                                                                  wax.     Wikipedia.https://en.wikipedia.

                                                                  org/wiki/Earwax  Professional, C. C.
                                                                  M. (n.d.). Earwax.  Cleveland  Clinic.
                                                                  https://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/
                                                                  body/24624-earwax









                                                                   Pereppaden Ancila Robinson

               Image 2: biological image of earwax






                                                           68


                                                                                  Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="78"><![CDATA[SMARTWATER










        INTRODUCTION



        Taggants  are a class of materials  that
        can be applied  to or incorporated  into
        an object to make it identifiable. This is
        done by producing individual and spe-

        cific batches of taggant with unique for-
        mulation, to make it unique and easy to
        detect once recovered. Thereby making
        themselves markers. When it comes to a                 Image 1. The cloth is subjected to SmartWater

        forensic taggant, it should be of low cost             emitting fluorescence under UV.  Credits: BBC
        to produce, be non-toxic to individuals
        and the environment, be simplistic and               protect antiques and national treasures which
        inexpensive to detect and easy to analyse            are under risk of being stolen. The application

        through non-destructive methods and be               of this technique to tackle domestic violence
        complex enough to prevent duplication.               is very new, thanks to Lee Berry, the detec-
        As these taggants are invisible to the na-           tive superintendent of West Yorkshire Police,
        ked eye, there is a need for localization            who came up with this implementation.

        to recover this back for analysis.  The
        easiest  and  effective  way  of  achieving
        this is by adding fluorescent compounds
        to it so that fluorescence can be achieved

        when they are introduced to UV or visi-
        ble spectrum.


        SMARTWATER



        SmartWater  technique  isn’t new to the
        crime  or forensic  spectrum,  we have
        been using this for a very long time

        to prevent burglary and deter thieves.                 Image 1. The cloth is subjected to SmartWater
        This technique  has been employed  to                 emitting fluorescence under UV.  Credits: BBC






                                                           69


        Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="79"><![CDATA[SmartWater  is a forensic theft  deterrent            Water produced, making this technique
        marketed  as  a  long-lasting,  traceable             valuable evidence.

        chemical taggant that contains distinctive,           As an initiative, The West Yorkshire Po-
        identifiable and traceable elemental com-             lice have given 200 women, the Smart-
        position, used to label valuable property             Water package, which consists of a hand-
        or monitor criminal activity. It is also used         held canister for spraying to use it like a
        as a biological marker.  The procedure of             pepper spray, there is a gel for door han-

        implementation  is simple, inexpensive,               dles and gates- when the someone touch-
        rapid, and environmentally safe. More-                es this surface, it immediately links them
        over, the detection for the presence of the           to the scene, and an automatic trap that

        mark does not require sample preparation              sprays if someone approaches the house
        or an assay. Each produced bottle or can-             under SmartWater protection.
        ister will have a unique composition of the
        components making it hard to duplicate,               This surely doesn’t prevent the crime
        by making each product unique, it is easy             from happening, to prevent the crime

        to locate categorically. The effectiveness            from happening warnings are given at
        of the product lies in the fact that it stays         various stages of attack to show that the
        on the skin for up to six weeks and lon-              victim is protected. This warning clearly

        ger on clothes. Domestic abuse is difficult           asks the perpetrator to deter but doesn’t
        to prove due to the lack of evidence and              inform the mechanism through which the
        eyewitnesses. If the culprit is forensically          victim is protected. But to feel safer, the
        marked, the association of the perpetrator            targeted or vulnerable women and men
        to the crime scene is clear, it also links the        are given the kit. The kit also contains

        perpetrator to the specific bath of Smart             stickers to be put in windows stating that
                                                              the house is protected by forensic mark-
                                                              ing. The canister containing the taggant

                                                              has a coverage up to 10m in distance.


                                                              STATISTICS



                                                              •  In 2014, Fort Lauderdale Police De-
                                                                  partment reported the use of Smart-
                                                                  Water  products  with  a  reduction  in
                                                                  burglaries of 14%.


          Image 3. Each bottle is filled with a differ-       •  SmartWater  has helped  bring  down
         ent and unique composition. Credits: BBC                 domestic burglary by 25 per cent in
                                                                  UK






                                                           70


                                                                               Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="80"><![CDATA[4.  Barbara Daniel a,  Vincenzo  Abbate
           CONCLUSION                                              b, Nunzianda Frascione, J. G. (2016).

                                                                   Taggant materials in forensic science:
           There is a rapid use of taggant to mark in              A review. TrAC Trends in Analytical
           a forensic perspective and has become a                 Chemistry, 83(Part B), 49-54. https://
           significant part of the national crime re-              doi.org/10.1016/j.trac.2016.08.003

           duction strategies. SmartWater helps to
           prevent  and  monitor  criminal  offences,           5.  L. B. (2022, June 7). Forensic mark-
           as this technique  is becoming  frequent                ing to protect victims of domestic
           to widespread to the public, there might                abuse. College of Policing. https://

           be a decrease in taggant efficiency as the              www.college.police.uk/article/foren-
           perpetrator or the offender is familiarised             sic-marking-protect-victims-domes-
           with this technique.                                    tic-abuse



           REFERENCES


           1.  Staff, F. (2022, February 21). In a first,
               SmartWater used to convict domes-

               tic  abuser: New way UK is protect-
              ing women. Firstpost. https://www.
              firstpost.com/world/in-a-first-smart-
              water-used-to-convict-domestic-abus-

              er-new-way-uk-is-protecting-wom-
              en-10395301.html

           2.  (2022, October  4). Domestic  Abuse                         A. Sherlin Gomez
              and SmartWater  Forensic Spray:
              Helping victims  rebuild their lives.

              IBBLAW. https://www.ibblaw.co.uk/
              insights/domestic-abuse-smartwa-
              ter-forensic-spray

           3.  McCallum, S. (2022, February 18).
              SmartWater: The forensic spray help-

              ing keep  women  safe. BBC. https://
              www.bbc.com/news/technolo-
              gy-60414452












                                                           71


      Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="81"><![CDATA[CASE STUDIES















                      1              The V     a mpir     e Ra    pist
                                     The Vampire Rapist









                                                             v
                                                               er killer
                                                 een Ri
                      2              The Green River killer
                                     The Gr






















































                                                         72                        Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="82"><![CDATA[THE VAMPIRE




                    RAPIST







        ‘The Vampire Rapist’s reign of terror in
        Ontario, Canada’



        Ontario, Canada experienced a very ter-
        rorizing period from the year 1969-1971
        when a serial killer went on a rampage

        killing and raping girls. As many serial
        killers used to leave a signature, he too
        left a bite on his victim’s breasts. Hence

        he got the moniker The Vampire Rapist.
        Wayne Clifford Boden was known as a
        quiet kid who played football in school.
        Boden used to go by the name ‘Bill’ and
        entrap these innocent girls by his charms.                                         Image(1)

        He was a sexual sadist who was driven
        with desire to bite female breasts. The in-              2.   Marielle Archambault
        vestigators saw that there were no signs                Marielle was a jewellery clerk who on No-
        of forced entry in the apartments of these              vember 23rd left work with ‘Bill’ who was

        girls who were found naked and decapi-                  introduced to her co-workers who pointed
        tated.                                                  out that Marielle was enthralled by him. The
                                                                next morning, Archambault didn’t show up
        These were the unfortunate girls: -                     to her workplace, so her employer went in

        1.  Shirley Audette                                     search of her to her apartment. Along with
        She was a 20-year-old who lived  with                   the landlady, they both found Marielle dead
        her boyfriend in Montreal and was found                 and she was fully clothed. They found the
        dead  in her apartment on October  3rd                  room to be well kept which indicated that

        1969. She lived  next  door to  Boden.                  there was no forced entry nor any strug-
        There were no signs of struggle and she                 gle.  The medical  report of  Archambault
        was wholly covered but upon investiga-                  was similar to that of Audette’s description.
        tion, the investigators found out that she              A photograph was found in the apartment

        had been raped and bitten on her breast                 which was confirmed by her co-worker that
        and that she was strangled to death.                    the person in the picture to be that of ‘Bill’





                                                           73


     Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="83"><![CDATA[3.   Jean Wray                                         The next day, May 19th, a patrolman
        After 2 months, Boden made an appear-                  found the  car  which  was under  suspi-

        ance  on January  16th 1970 where he                   cion.  The blue Mercedes was parked
        killed Jean Wray aged 24 in her Montreal               near the crime scene. The police arrested
        apartment. Wray was found dead by her                  Wayne Boden half an hour later when he
        boyfriend who had come to pick her up                  was walking towards the car. Boden ad-
        but got no response at first. He then came             mitted that the cufflink was his and that

        back again and this time  he found her                 he was indeed dating Elizabeth and had
        front door to be open, he rushed inside to             met her on the night that she was mur-
        find her naked and her breasts had bloody              dered. A cast had been made of Boden’s

        bite marks.                                            teeth which was compared with the bite
         4.   Elizabeth Pourteous                              marks that were present on the victims
        Elizabeth  Anne  Pourteous  who was 33                 by  an  Odonatologist.  This  proved  that
        years old was reported to be missing on                Boden was the man behind the rape and
        May 18th as she didn’t show up for work.               murder of these innocent girls and he ul-

        Hence, a call was placed to her apartment              timately attained life imprisonment.
        manager who then went up to her room
        only to discover the room to be in a mess                REFERENCES

        with her dead on her bedroom floor. She
        was raped  and decapitated  with evident               1]  Blanco,  J.  I.  (n.d.).  Wayne  Clifford
        bite marks on her breasts. The investiga-              Boden | Murderpedia, the encyclopedia
        tors found a cufflink which appeared to be             of murderers.  https://murderpedia.org/
        broken near the body. Pourteous was seen               male.B/b/boden-wayne.htm

        with a young looking fellow in a blue co-
        loured Mercedes on the night she died by               2] Bhb. (2022b, January 28). Serial Kill-
        2 of her colleagues. A friend of Elizabeth             er #2: Wayne Boden aka The Vampire

        pointed out that she had been going out                Rapist.       https://sites.psu.edu/beamer-
        with an acquaintance named  ‘Bill’  who                blog/2022/01/28/serial-killer-2-wayne-
        perfectly fit the descriptions of the Vam-             boden-aka-the-vampire-rapist/
        pire Rapist.








                                                                       Plathothathil Rachael

                                                                                  Rajath







                                                          74

                                                                                Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="84"><![CDATA[THE GREEN RIVER




              KILLER







      INTRODUCTION



      Gary Leon Ridgway, or the Green River
      Killer, is an American serial killer, necro-
      philiac, ephebophilia, and sex offender re-

      sponsible for murdering around 80 wom-
      en, half of whom were prostitutes, teenage
      girls,  and  other  women.  Ridgway  only
      confessed to 49 murders, which made him

      the second most prolific serial killer in the
      history of the United States, according to
      the confirmed murders during the 1980s
      and 1990s.



      BACKGROUND

                                                                Image 1: The accused Gary Leon Ridgway.
      Born dyslexic on February 18, 1949, in

      Salt Lake City, Utah, and raised in SeaT-                leading him into the woods. The boy sur-
      ac, Washington, His father, Thomas New-                  vived the attack. He also used to torture
      ton Ridgway, was a bus driver who used                   animals and had to redo a year in school.
      to criticise the prostitutes he saw on the               At age 18, Gary joined the Navy, served in

      streets. Mary Rita Ridgway was an abu-                   Vietnam, and married his girlfriend Clau-
      sive mother to her three children and her                dia Barrows, whom he later divorced due
      husband. She had the behaviour of wash-                  to extramarital affairs. He married Marcia
      ing young Gary’s genitals as he had the                  Winslow later in 1973, which also ended

      habit of wetting his bed, which continued                in divorce for the same reasons, though
      till his teenage years and led to Gary fan-              he had a son with her named  Matthew.
      tasising  about  killing  his mother.  When              She later claimed that he had placed her
      Ridgway was 16 years old, he stabbed a                   in a chokehold.

      boy through the ribs into his liver after





                                                           75

      Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="85"><![CDATA[According to most women in Ridge-                       deceased would reduce the need for a
        way’s life, he had a crazy sexual drive                  living victim,  thus reducing his pos-
        and would pressure them to have sexu-                    sibility of being caught. To avoid fo-

        al intercourse several times a day. Gary                 rensics leading to him, he would dump
        was a big hypocrite, as he enjoyed sex-                  garbage and other things on the dump
        ual services from sex workers but also                   sites and would occasionally transport
        complained about them frequently.                        bodies to other states.

        In 1988, he married his third wife, Ju-                  The Green River  Task Force was
        dith  Mawson, whom he  was still  mar-                   formed early in the 1980s to investigate
        ried to while his final arrest took place.               the murders. In 1984, Robert Keppel
        He shared a more intimate relationship                   and Dave Reichert interviewed the im-

        with her and had less urge to kill.                      prisoned serial killer Ted Bundy regu-
                                                                 larly. According to him, the killer was
        MURDERS                                                  returning to the dump sites to have sex

                                                                 with his victims,  which proved true,
        The majority of Ridgway’s murders start-                 and the police should stake out a new
        ed taking place in the 1980s and went                    grave and wait for the killer to return.
        on until the 1990s in the cities of Seattle
        and Tacoma.  Most victims  were either

        runaways or sex workers. Gary used to
        lure women by earning their trust using
        his son’s pictures, which eventually end-
        ed up with sexual intercourse and after-

        wards strangling the women by choking
        them. Most were killed in his truck, his
        house, or a very secluded area. He of-
        ten used to use his arms to choke, but in

        time, he started using belts, rope, fishing
        line socks, and even t-shirts and dumped
        their bodies, naked or in a pose, in riv-
        ers and the wilderness. Ridgway would

        sometimes go back to the dumped bod-
        ies and conduct sexual intercourse, not
        because he enjoyed it but because he be-
        lieved that having sex with the




                                                                            Image 2





                                                           76

                                                                                 Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="86"><![CDATA[He  was  identified  as  a  potential  culprit
                                                               in  the  Green  River  murders  in  1983.
                                                               Ridgway took and passed a lie detector
                                                               test  in 1984. In 1987, law  enforcement
                                                               obtained  hair  and  saliva  samples  from

                                                               him. Some samples collected  in 1987
                                                               were provided as evidence for Ridgway’s
                                                               arrest warrant, and he was finally arrested

                                                               at his workplace on November 30, 2001.
                                                               In a plea agreement that arrived in June,
                                                               Ridgway agreed to plead guilty to 48
                                                               charges  of  aggravated  first-degree  mur-
                                                               der in exchange for his cooperation  in

                                                               locating his victims and providing other
                                                               details. Ridgway pleaded guilty to the 48
                                                               charges on November 5, 2003. In 2003,

                                                               Ridgway was sentenced to serve 48 con-
                                                               secutive life sentences with no chance of
                                                               parole. Additionally, he received 10 years
                                                               for tampering with evidence in each of the
                                                               48 victims’ cases, which added up to 480

                                                               years. He currently resides at the Wash-
                                                               ington State Penitentiary.


                          Image 3

          Images 2 and 3: Information regard-

        ing the victims' disappearance and their
                      bodies recovered.





        CONFESSIONS AND ARREST



        Ridgway had been apprehended twice,
        in 1982 and 2001, for offences linked to
        prostitution.


                                                                          Image 4. Letter written by
                                                                              Gary Leon Ridgway.






                                                          77
        Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="87"><![CDATA[REFERENCES


                                                              1.  Wiki, C.  T. C. M. (n.d.-b). Gary

                                                                 Ridgway. Criminal Minds Wiki. https://
                                                                 criminalminds.fandom.com/wiki/
                                                                 Gary_Ridgway

                                                              2.  Wikipedia  contributors. (2023). Gary
                                                                 Ridgway. Wikipedia. https://en.wikipe-

                                                                 dia.org/wiki/Gary_Ridgway

                                                              3.  Tikkanen,  A.  (2023, July 30). Gary
                                                                 Ridgway | Biography, Mother, Child-
                                                                 hood, & Murders. Encyclopedia Britan-
                                                                 nica.  https://www.britannica.com/biog-

                                                                 raphy/Gary-Ridgway
                              Image 5                         4.  Image 1- Wikipedia Contributors. (2019,

                                                                 January 31). Gary Ridgway. Wikipedia;
                                                                 Wikimedia Foundation. https://en.wiki-
                                                                 pedia.org/wiki/Gary_Ridgway


                                                              5.  Images 2 and 3-  Wikipedia  contribu-
                                                                 tors. (2023). Gary Ridgway. Wikipedia.
                                                                 https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gary_
                                                                 Ridgway

                                                              6.  Images 4 and 5- Gary Ridgway. (2000).

                                                                 Criminal  Minds  Wiki. https://crim-
                                                                 inalminds.fandom.com/wiki/Gary_
                                                                 RidgwayImage 6- Gary Leon Ridgeway
                                                                 “Green River Killer.” (n.d.). Pinterest.
                                                                 https://www.pinterest.com/serialkiller-

                                                                 projects/gary-leon-ridgeway-green-riv-
                                                                 er-killer/




                              Image 6
               Images 5 and 6: Photographs of                              Anashwara Pramod
                         Gary's victims.                                 Allen Jose Tomyachen







                                                          78

                                                                                 Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="88"><![CDATA[FEATURE ARTICLE















                                     The Gaze of Truth: How Eyewitness
                      1              The Ga       ze of T      r ut  h: Ho     w Ey     ewit    ness
                                     T
                                     Testimonies Shape Forensic Verdicts
                                                                            or
                                                                                                      t
                                                                                             er
                                                                                                        s
                                                                                                 dic
                                                                                ensic V
                                        estimonies Shape F
                                      Cracking Cases From The Clouds:
                      2               Cr  ac  king Ca       ses Fr     om The Clouds:
                                                                        one F
                                                                                      ensics
                                                      nce Of Dr
                                                                                  or
                                      Significance Of Drone Forensics
                                      Significa



                                      Forensic Genetic Genealogy
                      3               F or  ensic Genetic Genealog                     y









                      4               AI In Digital Forensics
                                                                    ensics
                                                                or
                                      AI In Digita
                                                           l F





                       5             Kevlar – The Reinforced Ballistic Vest
                                                                                                      est
                                                                                      allist
                                                                                               ic V
                                          v
                                            la
                                     K
                                        e
                                                r – The R
                                                                        or
                                                                            ced B
                                                                 einf












                                                         79
       Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="89"><![CDATA[THE GAZE OF TRUTH:



   HOW EYEWITNESS TESTIMONIES



   SHAPE FORENSIC VERDICTS








        INTRODUCTION


        In the realm of criminal justice, eyewit-

        ness testimonies have long held a prom-
        inent position. These firsthand accounts
        from individuals who claim to have wit-
        nessed a crime have historically played a

        significant role in shaping forensic ver-
        dicts. However, as our understanding of
        memory, perception,  and the fallibility
        of human observation deepens, the im-

        pact of eyewitness testimonies on legal
        outcomes is being critically reevaluated.
        Eyewitness testimonies are more than
        mere  statements  – they are windows

        into the human experience  of crime.                                       Image 1
        They recount the visceral reactions, the
        heart-pounding  moments, and  the  fear                  Rather, it is a complex and malleable con-
        that  grips  individuals  when  they  find               struct that can be influenced by a myriad

        themselves  unwittingly  cast in the role                of factors. Emotions, stress, suggestibility,
        of observer to unlawful acts. Their narra-               and the passage of time can all distort the
        tives offer glimpses into the lives of vic-              accuracy of recall. This inherent fragility
        tims, the minds of perpetrators, and the                 of memory casts a shadow of doubt over

        web of events that led to the courtroom                  the  reliability  of eyewitness  testimonies.
                                                                 While  eyewitnesses  may  be  completely

        The Fallibility  of Memory: Human                        sincere  in their  recollections,  the  nature
        memory  is not an  infallible  record  of                of memory makes it susceptible to distor-

        events. Rather, it is a complex and mal-                 tions, leading to potentially erroneous ac-
        leable  construct  that  can  be  influenced             counts of events.
        by a myriad of factors.



                                                           80


                                                                                 Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="90"><![CDATA[The Power of Suggestion: Eyewitness-                 Memory  Reconstruction and Cogni-

        es can be unintentionally influenced by              tive Biases: Memory is not a static play-
        external cues, such as leading questions             back of past events but rather a dynamic
        from investigators or media coverage of              process of reconstruction. In recalling an
        the crime. The mere presence of author-              event,  individuals  fill  in  gaps  with  as-
        ity  figures  during  identification  proce-         sumptions, perceptions, and even infor-

        dures can lead witnesses to make choices             mation acquired after the fact. Cognitive
        based on implicit cues, rather than their            biases,  such  as  confirmation  bias  or  the
        true recollection. Such instances under-             tendency to see what one expects to see,

        score the need for meticulously designed             further contribute to the distortion of eye-
        procedures to minimise suggestive influ-             witness accounts.
        ences.
                                                             Consider  a  witness  who  sees  a  fleeting
        In one study, participants were shown a              glimpse of a suspect during a high-stress

        video of a staged crime. Afterward, they             situation. Their  mind may  unconscious-
        were asked leading questions that con-               ly fill in details to create a more coherent
        tained false information about the event.            narrative. Over time, these reconstructed

        Shockingly, many participants  incor-                details become intertwined with the orig-
        porated this fabricated information into             inal memory, blurring the line between
        their  accounts when questioned  later.              what was actually witnessed and what the
        This phenomenon, known as the mis-                   witness believes was witnessed.
        information effect, highlights how even

        well-meaning witnesses can be suscepti-
        ble to suggestion, leading to the creation
        of false memories.












                                                                                  Image 3

                                                              Unconscious  Transference and  Mis-

                                                              identification:  Eyewitnesses may  inad-
                                                              vertently misidentify innocent individuals
                                                              due to a phenomenon known as uncon-
                            Image 2                           scious transference.







                                                           81


                                                                                  Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="91"><![CDATA[This occurs when a familiar  face from                 are  adopting reforms to  mitigate  poten-

        another  context  is incorrectly  associated           tial injustices. Sequential lineups, which
        with the crime scene. The witness genu-                present suspects one at a time  instead
        inely  believes  they saw the  perpetrator,            of in a group, also help prevent relative
        even though the person was not involved.               judgments that might occur in simultane-
        Such  misidentifications  can  have  dire              ous lineups. Moreover, some jurisdictions

        consequences  for both  the  accused  and              are implementing expert testimony on the
        the pursuit of justice.                                fallibility  of human memory during tri-
        Imagine a scenario where a witness rec-                als. Forensic psychologists and experts in

        ognizes a person from their neighbour-                 human memory now play a critical role
        hood in a police  lineup.  Unbeknownst                 in courtrooms, educating judges and ju-
        to the witness, they had seen this person              ries  about  the  fallibility  of eyewitness
        at a store a few days prior to the crime.              accounts.  By explaining the  science  of
        Despite the absence of any criminal  in-               memory, cognitive biases, and the poten-

        volvement, the witness identifies the in-              tial  for  misidentification,  these  experts
        nocent individual due to the blurred lines             help decision-makers critically  evaluate
        between memory and recognition.                        the weight they give to eyewitness testi-

                                                               monies.


                                                               CONCLUSION



                                                               The gaze of truth is a powerful concept,
                                                               but it is one tempered by the complex na-
                                                               ture of human memory and perception.
                                                               While eyewitness testimonies have histor-

                                                               ically held sway in forensic verdicts, their
                                                               role is now under scrutiny. The delicate
                                                               balance between justice and the potential
                                                               for error necessitates a multidisciplinary

                                                               approach that incorporates the latest find-
                                                               ings from psychology, neuroscience, and
                          Image 4
                                                               forensic science. As legal systems evolve
                                                               to embrace more informed and scientif-

                                                               ic approaches, the path to truth becomes
        Reforming the Legal Landscape: Rec-                    clearer, ensuring that the pursuit of justice
        ognizing the limitations of eyewitness tes-            is not compromised by the fragility of hu-

        timonies, legal systems around the world               man memory.








                                                           82



     Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="92"><![CDATA[While eyewitness testimonies will like-                4.  Image 1 :https://www.sjpl.org/blog/
         ly always have a place in the courtroom,                  source-reliable-join-learning-circle

         understanding their limitations empow-
         ers us to interpret  them  with caution,               5.   Image  2:  Importance  of Right
         ensuring that the pursuit of justice re-                  Knowledge. (n.d.).  The New In-
         mains steadfast even in the face of the                   dian  Express. Retrieved  Septem-
         imperfections of human perception and                     ber 29, 2023, from https://www.
         memory.                                                   newindianexpress.com/lifestyle/

                                                                   spirituality/2021/dec/26/impor-
                                                                   tance-of-right-knowledge-2399029.
                                                                   html

                                                                6.   Image  4:  Flag Frame Illustration
                                                                   28992808 - Megapixl. (n.d.). Www.

                                                                   megapixl.com.  Retrieved  Septem-
                                                                   ber 29, 2023, from https://www.
                                                                   megapixl.com/flag-frame-illustra-
                                                                   tion-28992808







                          Image 5


        REFERENCES



        1.  Johnson, M. R., &  Williams,  L. S.
            (2021). Eyewitness  Testimonies and
            Their Influence on Forensic Verdicts.
            Journal of Legal  Psychology, 35(2),

            145-162.                                                       Riya Ghosh

        2.  Smith  (2022). Memory  and Percep-
            tion in Court: Rethinking the Impact
            of Eyewitness Testimonies. Forensic
            Science Review, 12(4), 281-298.

        3.  Legal  Insights Group. (2023).  The

            Fallibility of Eyewitness Testimonies:
            Implications  for the  Justice  System.
            Legal Insights Journal, 45(1), 58-71.






                                                           83



                                                                                   Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="93"><![CDATA[CRACKING CASES FROM




      THE CLOUDS:



      SIGNIFICANCE OF DRONE




           FORENSICS








       In the rapidly growing domain of technol-
       ogy, the skies have now become the new
       limit not only for innovation and investi-

       gation but also modern mediums for of-
       fenders to perform unlawful activities.
       Drones,  also referred to as Unmanned
       Aerial Vehicles (UAVs), are flying robots

       that are remotely controlled or can fly on
       their own using flight plans that are con-
       trolled by a radio controller which is prac-                                    Image 1
       tically a handheld device by software and

       onboard sensors and a global positioning                  •  Smuggling of illegal substances, drugs,
       system (GPS).                                                 weapons, etc.
                                                                 •  It’s widely used as an instrument that

       Drones when we usually think about our                        leads  to  terrorism  by putting  in  the

       day-to-day  life  the  first  application  that               ground into stadiums and other public
       comes  to  our minds  is  for photography                     gatherings.
       and videography purposes. Nevertheless,                   •  One of the most common illegal uses of
       drones are being used in a plethora of sec-                   drones is that they are used to intrude

       tors, right from the military for security                    into  one’s personal  space and capture
       purposes to criminals for illegal activities                  private images and video recordings of
       and hence it also marked the start of a very                  individuals and later use these record-
       engrossing field called drone forensics.                      ings against them and blackmail them.
                                                                 •  Stalking, harassing, and other unethical

       Some of the many illegal uses of drones                       reporting is another illegal application
       may include:                                                  of drones.





                                                           84


       Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="94"><![CDATA[RELEVANCY OF DRONE                                   •  Intention and motive of that particular
        FORENSICS                                                flight.

                                                             •  Atmospheric conditions.
        Today society places a high value  on
        drone forensics. With adequate training              It also reveals data such as GPS status,
        and equipment,  a forensic data analyst              Wi-fi data, Drone serial number, Internet

        can extract  plenty  of data  from one of            protocol (IP), Bluetooth, 3G and 4G con-
        such drones that has been seized by a fo-            nectivity status, and Pilot control output.
        rensic team.                                         Just as a wise man once said, ‘Nothing
        This device is then prepared for exam-               is perfect in this world, everything has its

        ination and gathers crucial digital shreds           pros and cons’ hence this amazing field of
        of evidence that can reveal many facts               drone forensics has its limitations.
        about that particular case.



        A drone operates similarly to a computer,
        in addition to having a central processing
        unit (CPU), Universal Serial Bus (USB)
        ports and a data storage device like a Se-

        cure Digital (SD) card, camera, and oth-
        er sensors may also be added to it. This
        enables a digital forensic film analyst to
        utilise cutting-edge techniques like VIP

        2.0 to put together the events using the
        footage captured throughout the trip and
        recover the missing details. A digital fo-               [Image 2: Working of drone forensics]
        rensic investigator must adhere to strin-

        gent criteria and industry standards for             The challenges faced by drone forensic
        the information recovered from drones                investigators are:
        to be admitted into evidence in court.               •  Damage caused to the storage media

                                                                 and scattering components. This may
        Crucial data that can be retrieved from a                include cases if the drone has been
        drone includes:                                          damaged during the flight or because
        •  Images/Videos captured                                the landing was not appropriately
        •  Landing,  launching,  returning,  and                 done.

            home location.                                   •  High  cost  of  investment  and  mainte-

                                                                 nance.







                                                           85


                                                                                   Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="95"><![CDATA[•  Lack of GPS information.                            REFERENCES
        •  Not all flights will have great connec-             1.  Al-Room, K., Iqbal, F., Baker,  T.,

            tivity. There might be instances where                Shah, B., Yankson, B., MacDermott,
            the GPS signal will be lost.                          A., & Hung, P. C. K. (2021). Drone
        •  Absence of suitable digital forensic                   Forensics. International  Journal of
            instruments.                                          Digital  Crime  and Forensics, 13(1),
        •  Trouble  connecting  to  the  drone’s                  1–25.         https://doi.org/10.4018/ijd-

            USB port.                                             cf.2021010101
        Points to be noted during the search and               2.  Expert Code Lab Pvt. Ltd., www.
        seizure of suspected drones:                              expertcodelab.com.  (n.d.). Forensic

        •  If the drone is on, take images of the                 Handwriting Expert,  Fingerprint  Ser-
            controller’s display then switch the                  vice, crime investigation, Cyber Foren-
            drone and its components off.                         sic, Signature analysis lab India, ques-
        •  The  investigator  must identify  the                  tioned  document,  cross examination
            mode of communication between the                     - Drone Forensics: The Modern Tech-

            controller and the drone.                             nology. Learn Forensic. https://www.
        •  Identify the make and model of the                     sifsindia.com/index.php/blog-de-
            drone.                                                tails/Drone-Forensics:-The-Mod-

        •  Isolate the drone from GPS satellites                  ern-Technology/99#:~:text=It%20
            and other devices to ensure that GPS                  involves%20bring%20out%20
            signals are not picked.                               and,%2C%20geolocations%2C%20
        •  A search for any external storage de-                  unique%20ID%20etc
            vices such as SD cards should be con-

            ducted.                                            3.  Image 1: Google Image Result. (n.d.).
        •  Photograph and label the status of the                 Www.google.com. Retrieved Septem-
            drone and its components.                             ber 27, 2023, from https://images.app.
                                                                  goo.gl/CQ6kCgyEXRpDrB2x9

        CONCLUSION:                                            4.   Image 2: Title:  Sustainability  | Free
        Concerns about privacy invasions, illegal                 Full-Text | Drone Forensics and Ma-
        and malicious use of drones, among To                     chine Learning: Sustaining the Inves-
        gather important forensic evidence about                  tigation Process. (n.d.). Www.google.

        an incident involving the drone, it is nee-               com.  Retrieved  September  27, 2023,
        dactions recorded inside the drone during                 from https://images.app.goo.gl/oEDT-
        ed for the digital investigator to possess                tAtvz1mmZbU58

        the knowledge and comprehension of the
        key processes, characteristics, and func-
        tionalities of drones.


                                                                            Sasha Vassula

                                                                               Fernandes

                                                           86


        Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="96"><![CDATA[FORENSIC GENETIC




         GENEALOGY









       INTRODUCTION


       Forensic Genetic Genealogy (FGG), also

       known as Investigative Genetic Geneal-
       ogy,  is one of the most unique forensic
       investigative tools that emerged in 2018
       which uses the conventional methods of

       genealogy  and  genetics  to  identify  the
       perpetrator  of a heinous crime.  FGG  is
       based on the  fundamental  principle  of
       genetics  that an individual will share a

       common DNA with their ancestors and
       if  there  is  a  generational  gap  between
       the individuals, they can still carry some                                     Image:1
       amount of the same DNA. DNA can play

       a very crucial role in solving cases such                 tests help to know if two families are relat-
       as violent crimes or even cases of missing                ed. Now we can look for people who
       or unidentified individuals.                              are not just related through the male line

                                                                 but also the female line. The case of the
       EMERGENCE OF FGG                                          Golden State killer is considered to be the
                                                                 birth of Forensic Genetic Genealogy. He
       Genetic genealogy uses DNA typing and                     committed over 50 rapes and 200 burglar-
       DNA testing in  combination  with  con-                   ies from 1974 to 1976 and was unidentified

       ventional genealogy methods to find the                   for a long time. After more than 40 years
       relationships between individuals. Earlier                of  being  unidentified,  the  golden  stake
       genealogy  started  using  Y chromosome                   killer was finally found using GEDmatch,
       testing in which the Y chromosome that                    a genealogy site with a genetic database.

       was passed down by the male line was
       used to identify individuals. People study
       surnames and build a family tree. These






                                                           87


                                                                                 Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="97"><![CDATA[marriage  and hence he/she might share
        HOW DOES FGG WORK?
                                                               some DNA from both families. The work
                                                               is carried out by genetic  genealogists
        FGG collects  DNA from an unknown
        sample encountered at a crime scene and                along with investigators to narrow down
        does DNA typing to establish the identi-               to a set of individuals based on informa-

        ty and family relationship of the individ-             tion  predicted  such as the  perpetrator’s
        ual. This is then uploaded to the Genet-               gender, hair, and eye colour. Once a per-
        ic Genealogy database which previously                 son is suspicious, his/her  DNA sample
        has stored the DNA of many individuals.                is collected  and  compared  with  that  of

        FGG compares the unknown DNA with                      the unknown sample collected from the
        the  database  and looks for people  who               crime scene.
        share a certain amount of DNA with the
        perpetrator. Based on the amount of DNA                HOW IS FGG USEFUL IN SOLVING

        shared, the perpetrator could be a close or            CRIMES?
        even a distant relative of the person with
        a match. These genetic matches are taken               FGG has a broad reach into the data. The
        and a genetic tree is built. For example,              most common type of DNA profiling used

        there is a family A which got married into             by forensics in criminal cases is called
        family B. There is a huge possibility that             Short Tandem Repeat (STR). It is used to
        the perpetrator could be a descendant of               identify  missing individuals  and also  to
        that,                                                  link a suspect to a crime scene. Howev-
                                                               er, DNA STR analysis can only provide
                                                               connections to close relatives and not to
                                                               distant ones. Whereas, single nucleotide
                                                               polymorphisms (SNP) used in FGG help

                                                               to  identify  the  paternal  lineages  from
                                                               deep ancestry. The SNP data obtained is
                                                               uploaded to the genetic genealogy data-
                                                               base in which the DNA of those members

                                                               who have voluntarily provided their DNA
                                                               for SNP analysis is present. The unknown
                                                               SNP data is compared with other mem-
                                                               ber’s SNP data and a list of people who

                                                               share the DNA with the unknown person
                                                               is generated.

                            Image:2









                                                           88


      Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="98"><![CDATA[CASES SOLVED USING FGG                                 3.  Forensic     Science      International:

                                                                   Genetics,  53, 102525. https://doi.
         •  Murder and sexual assault of Jodi                      org/10.1016/j.fsigen.2021.102525
            Loomis,1972:  The  case  of Jodi
            Loomis remained  unsolved for al-                   4.  Forensic Investigative genetic  ge-
            most 47 years. Jodi Loomis’s body                      nealogy. (2023, March 10). Leiden
            was identified on August 23, 1972,                     Law Blog. https://www.leidenlaw-
            with DNA evidence  preserved  on                       blog.nl/articles/forensic-investiga-
            her body and boots. Years later, DNA                   tive-genetic-genealogy

            genetic  genealogy  was  utilised  to               5.  Aldrick, A. (2022). Case  File: The
            identify 78-year-old Terrance Miller
            as the killer                                          Golden State Killer — Forensic Sci-
         •  16-year-old double murder in Swe-                      ence Society. Forensic Science So-
            den:  On October 19, 2004, an eight-                   ciety.
            year-old boy and a fifty-six-year-old               6.  https://forensicsciencesociety.com/
            woman  were  stabbed  to  death  in                    thedrip/case-file-the-golden-state-
            the city of Linkoping, Sweden. Af-                     killer
            ter 15 years of investigation, DNA

            sets were formed and searched with                  7.  Image 2- Imgur. (n.d.). imgur.com.
            databases of GEDmatch and Family                       Imgur. Retrieved  September 29,
            tree DNA genealogy. FGG helped to                      2023, from https://imgur.com/92O-
            identify two brothers, one of whom                     3zOR
            matched with DNA taken from the
            crime scene.



         REFERENCES


         1.  Glynn, C. L. (2022). Bridging disci-
            plines to form a new one: the emer-
            gence of forensic genetic genealo-
            gy. Genes, 13(8), 1381. https://doi.                         Riya Thookkanal
            org/10.3390/genes13081381                                              Reji

         2.  Tillmar,  A., Fagerholm, S., Staaf,
            J., Sjölund, P., & Ansell, R. (2021).
            Getting the conclusive lead with in-

            vestigative  genetic  genealogy  –  A
            successful case study of a 16-year-
            old double murder in Sweden.








                                                           89


                                                                                   Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="99"><![CDATA[AI IN DIGITAL



               FORENSICS







        INTRODUCTION



        The study of digital forensics is vital to
        identifying  and  combating  cybercrimes
        in the modern digital age, where infor-
        mation  and communication  technolo-

        gy have permeated every aspect of our
        lives.  Traditional  methods of analysis
        are losing their effectiveness as the com-
        plexity and volume of digital data con-

        tinue to rise. In this situation, artificial
        intelligence (AI) transforms the field of
        digital forensics. In this essay, we exam-
        ine the numerous applications of AI in

        digital  forensics to strengthen cyberse-
        curity and improve investigations.
                                                                                        Image 1
        UTILISING AI IN DIGITAL

        FORENSIC                                                 Automated data recovery
                                                                 Tools that are AI-powered help speed up

        AI-Assisted Evidence Analysis                            the process of recovering data from digi-
        The enormous volume of data that needs                   tal devices. These programs are capable of

        to be sorted through throughout an inves-                reassembling  fragmented  data,  retrieving
        tigation is one of the most difficult prob-              deleted files, and even obtaining data from
        lems in digital forensics. Large datasets                corrupted storage media. Digital forensic
        may be quickly analysed by AI-driven                     specialists can recover more data in less

        algorithms,  which  aids investigators  in               time  by using  AI algorithms, which in-
        finding patterns, anomalies, and possible                creases the effectiveness of investigations.
        evidence.  Predictive  modelling,  made                  Behavioural Analysis
        possible by machine learning techniques,                 By examining patterns and actions, AI can

        assists in  predicting  upcoming  cyber-                 understand the behaviour of digital  ob-
        threats and spotting potential weakness-                 jects, such as malware. This makes it pos-
        es before they are used against you.                     sible


                                                           90


        Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="100"><![CDATA[to spot harmful activity and create stron-           Detecting deep fakes, where AI-generated

        ger defences against it. Investigators can           media is used to create misleading or false
        play the cat and mouse game of cyber-                information, is a challenging task that AI
        crime  by using AI to comprehend  and                algorithms can help address. By analys-
        anticipate attacker behaviour.                       ing metadata, pixel-level alterations, and
        Natural Language Processing  (NLP)                   inconsistencies,  digital  forensic experts

        for Communication Analysis                           can determine the authenticity of visual
        With the proliferation of digital commu-             evidence.
        nication  platforms, analysing text  and             Ethical considerations and Challenges

        conversations has become a critical as-              While incorporating AI into digital foren-
        pect of digital forensics. NLP, a subfield           sics has many advantages, there are also
        of AI, enables the extraction of meaning-            some difficulties. The possibility for bias
        ful insights from vast amounts of textual            in AI systems, which could produce unre-
        data. This is particularly useful in detect-         liable findings, is a serious worry. To keep

        ing cyberbullying, online fraud, and oth-            investigations’ integrity, it  is crucial  to
        er forms of digital misconduct.                      guarantee the fairness and dependability
                                                             of these algorithms. When using AI tech-
                                                             nologies  in digital  forensic  procedures,

                                                             it’s also important  to carefully  evaluate
                                                             ethical issues related to privacy and data
                                                             protection.



                                                             CONCLUSION


                                                             By combining AI and digital  forensics,
                                                             we might potentially improve the effec-

                                                             tiveness,  accuracy,  and  proactiveness  of
                                                             cybercrime investigations. AI is proving
                                                             to be a helpful ally for digital  forensic
                                                             specialists, automating data recovery pro-
                            Image 2                          cedures,  assessing multimedia  content,


        Image and Video Analysis                             and foreseeing cyber dangers. To ensure
        AI-powered  image  and  video  analysis              that AI-driven investigations respect the
        tools assist in the examination of multi-            ideals of justice and fairness in our in-
        media files to identify forged or altered            creasingly digital society, it is vital to es-
        content.                                             tablish a balance  between technological
                                                             breakthroughs and ethical issues.






                                                           91


                                                                               Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="101"><![CDATA[REFERENCES


        1.  www.referencegate.net

        2.  www.sciencedirect.com

        3.  www.intechopen.com

        4.  Image  1: https //media.licdn.com/dms/

            image/C5612AQGv7I5_hAzwzQ/arti-
            cle-cover_image-shrink_600_2000/0/1
            559123270136?e=2147483647&v=beta
            &t=4YvxEUaO2a3jnzctu2jikUe6RWB-

            5Dt6SRPi2sQBUgX4

        5.  Image  2: https //images.app.goo.gl/
            VT2tKVBZHfbBg7wq8


































                                                                           Shreya Gupta





















                                                           92


     Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="102"><![CDATA[KEVLAR –



      THE REIFORCED BALLISTIC




                    VEST








       INTRODUCTION



       Testing and evaluating bulletproof vests
       and  jackets—commonly  referred  to  as
       “soft body armor”—is one of the crucial
       tasks assigned to the forensic examin-
       er. This element falls under the realm of

       ‘terminal ballistics’. One of the essential
       items of security equipment that law en-
       forcement  and corrections professionals

       require for personal protection  is body                  Image.1 Military armour vest made from
       armour. Lightweight body armour was                                      Kevlar material.
       first developed by the National Institute
       of Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice
       in 1971, and testing on it commenced in

       1978.  ‘Super  fibres’,  which  were  intro-
       duced by DuPont, are generally regarded                  when it  collides  with a bullet  or other
       as the biggest advancement in soft body                  low-velocity projectile. It is a well-known

       armour.                                                  para-aramid fibre that is mostly utilised in
       Kevlar has a high tensile  strength-to-                  fabric-braced  radial  tires. Because  of its
       weight ratio and is best recognised for its              resilience,  this  fibre  could  be  utilised  to
       usage in ballistic body armour, but it also              create soft body armour that is resistant to
       has many other uses. Kevlar is exception-                bullets. The fibres are woven into sheets

       ally robust due to the many interchange-                 using various yarn thicknesses. Kevlar, the
       able bonds in its molecular structure. Its               multi-layer web of woven fabrics, catches
       fibres are tightly spun, making it impos-

       sible  to  separate  them.  Kevlar’s strands
       grab and absorb the projectile’s energy






                                                           93


                                                                                  Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="103"><![CDATA[the bullet and provides protection as body             THE  ADVANTAGES OF KEVLAR

        armour.  The density of the weave, also                VEST
        known as denier, gives it the required
        properties. The sheets are securely sewn               Kevlar body armour provides ballistic
        into a vest-shaped container. Kevlar is a              protection,  and the extra layer  also ex-
        lightweight, highly functional, and flexi-             tends  to  some  rifle  ammunition.  These

        ble jacket. This is designed to essentially            vests are dependable, lightweight materi-
        stop any handgun missile.                              al, which makes them the perfect option
                                                               for a variety of settings and circumstanc-


        The main focus of terminal  ballistics  is             es.  Due  to  the  material  utilised  histori-
        the behaviour of the bullet after impact.              cally  as protective  panels, such as steel
        It largely focuses on the investigation of             plates, bulletproof panels have always
        missile and bullet penetration into various            been hefty. The DuPont business discov-
        target categories. This involves the study             ered Kevlar in the 1970s after extensive

        of bullet-resistant materials such as jack-            research. Kevlar has been demonstrated
        ets and vests. The implementation of Kev-              to be significantly stronger than steel be-
        lar  technology  in  ballistics  applications          cause  of  its  robustness and  lightweight,

        has enhanced safety for law enforcement                as well as after further development and
        officers.                                              testing.  This enables its application  in
                                                               ballistic body armour. These Kevlar pan-
                                                               els come in several levels of protection,

                                                               allowing  armour wearers to choose the
                                                               amount that best suits their requirements.
                                                               To  keep  these  Kevlar  vests  as  effective
                                                               as possible, they should be handled and
                                                               stored appropriately.



                                                               THE DISADVANTAGES OF KEV-
                                                               LAR VEST



                                                               Bulky  and Heavy:  Kevlar  body armour
                                                               can be fairly heavy and bulky, which in
         Image.2 Kevlar fibres used in manufac-                some circumstances may impair  move-
                   turing of body armour
                                                               ment and agility.



                                                               Water  Absorption:  When exposed to
                                                               damp conditions, Kevlar has a tendency

                                                               to absorb water, which can lower its






                                                           94


        Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="104"><![CDATA[ballistic performance and add weight to
         the fibre.                                              REFERENCES



         Despite being effective against the ma-                 1.  Google Scholar. (n.d.). https://
         jority of frequent threats, Kevlar body                    scholar.google.com/schol -

         armour  has limits  when dealing  with                     ar?hl=en&as_sdt=0%2C5&q=kev-
         numerous high-velocity  strikes in a                       lar+used+in+body+armor+ballis-
         small space.                                               tics&oq=kevlar+used+in+body+arq
                                                                    abs&t=1692729484554&u=%23p%
         Poor compressive strength: hard to be                      3DjJDoH97irBMJ

         crushed or squeezed; more sensitive to                  2.  Field,  F., &  Field,  F. (2021).  Ter-
         environmental factors than other mate-                     minal Ballistics - Forensic’s blog.
         rials.                                                     Forensic’s Blog. https://forensic-

                                                                    field.blog/terminal-ballistics/#:~:-
         Requires specially-made scissors to cut                    text=The%20Kevlar%20fibers%20
         dry fabric.  Once laminated,  only  spe-                   were%20simply,the%20form%20
         cially designed drill bits will penetrate                  of%20a%20vest
         it. Kevlar leverages its ability to deflect             3.  Kevlar Technology: Designed to de-

         bullets when wet as well as being high-                    feat today’s threats | Office of Justice
         ly vulnerable to many common home                          Programs. (n.d.). https://www.ojp.
         chemicals.                                                 gov/ncjrs/virtual-library/abstracts/

                                                                    kevlar-technology-designed-de-
         CONCLUSION                                                 feat-todays-threats


         Kevlar has a long shelf life and can last
         for a very long time with proper care.

         Since  its  creation,  Kevlar  has  saved
         countless lives, particularly in the field
         of law enforcement. Body armour is an-

         ticipated to get even lighter, more flex-
         ible, and more comfortable as technol-
         ogy develops. We appreciate Stephanie
         Kwolek for her work. Today, Kevlar is
         still demonstrating its value!














                                                           95


                                                                                 Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="105"><![CDATA[4.  The Advantages and Disadvantag-                     7.  Adams, R. (2020, March  10). How
            es of Kevlar vs UHMWPE Body Ar-                         does a Bullet-Proof vest work? Spec-
            mor. (n.d.). Military Depot. https://                   trum News 1. https://spectrumnews1.

            militarydepotusa.com/blog/the-ad-                       com/ca/la-west/news/2020/03/10/
            vantages-and-disadvantages-of-kev-                      how-does-a-bullet-proof-vest-work-
            lar-vs-uhmwpe-body-armor/#:~:-                          #:~:text=It’s%20not%20100%20per-
            text=Disadvantages%20of%20                              cent%20effective,the%20layers%20

            Kevlar%20Body%20Armor%3A&-                              of%20the%20Kevlar
            text=Water%20Absorption%3A%20
            Kevlar%20has%20a,when%20ex-
            posed%20to%20wet%20conditions

        5.  How does Kevlar® work? | Why is

            Kevlar®  so strong?  (2023, May 17).
            Explain  That  Stuff.  https://www.ex-
            plainthatstuff.com/kevlar.html

        6.  Nichols,  T.  (2021).  Benefits  of  a
            Kevlar®  vest. SafeGuard Clothing

            US.      https://www.safeguardclothing.
            com/blogs/articles/benefits-of-a-kev-
            lar%C2%AE-vest#:~:text=Body%20
            armor%20made%20from%20Kev-

            lar,in%20different%20environ-
            ments%20and%20scenarios






                                                                                 Anna Roy

                                                                               Naveena Joy

























                                                           96


    Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="106"><![CDATA[LITERATURE REVIEW















                                                      nced F
                                                                  or
                                                                      ensic Medicine And
                                     AI- Enha
                      1              AI- Enhanced Forensic Medicine And
                                          xicolog
                                                       y
                                     Toxicology
                                     T
                                        o

                      2               Digital Steganography As A Threat
                                                                             y As A Thr
                                                                        ph
                                                                                                    t
                                                                                                ea
                                                                      a
                                                       eganogr
                                      Digit
                                               al St


















































                                                         97                       Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="107"><![CDATA[AI- ENHANCED FORENSIC




        MEDICINE AND TOXICOLOGY








           ABSTRACT                                           medical expertise within legal frameworks.



           Artificial  intelligence  (AI)  is  identi-        Toxicology delves into understanding how
           fied as a specialised branch in software           various  chemicals  impact  human  health,

           engineering that examines how com-                 with sub-disciplines including clinical tox-
           puter systems emulate human actions                icology  for toxin-related  illness,  medical
           and cognitive processes. Researchers               toxicology for poison treatment. Occupa-
           might eventually build systems capa-               tional  toxicology focuses on health  risks

           ble of understanding and reasoning                 posed by toxic substances, analytical tox-
           about anything ahead of humans. AI                 icology for poison detection, and forensic
           will play a key role in framing various            toxicology for legal contexts.
           opinions of medicolegal importance.

           Advanced software has streamlined                  REVIEW
           forensic inquiries, elucidated the di-
           verse rationale behind various algo-               Conventional forensic analysis uses phys-
           rithms,  and diminished  errors aris-              ical data for age, gender, and facial assess-

           ing  from  cognitive  prejudices.  Yet,            ment, employing medical, biological, and
           no technology is exempt from con-                  mathematical  assessments  for  identifica-
           straints.  Intelligent  systems,  for in-          tion.  Investigator  expertise  is  influenced
           stance, demand extensive knowledge                 by factors like fatigue and emotions, im-

           databases,  potentially leading  to  in-           pacting undesirable forensic outcomes. AI
           correct conclusions when inputs devi-              can mitigate  time-intensive  and potential
           ate from trained datasets, resulting in            issues in this approach.
           false positives or negatives.

                                                              AI has triggered a fundamental transforma-
           PROLOGUE                                           tion within the realm of medical sciences,
                                                              enabling precise diagnosis, individualised
           AI is a pillar for all digital transforma-         treatment  strategies,  and  heightened  pa-

           tions. AI is overarching in the field of           tient  well-being.  Machine  learning  (ML)
           toxicology to analyze biological sam-              algorithms possess the capability to metic-
           ples. Forensic medicine applies                    ulously analyse extensive datasets, facili-




                                                           98

      Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="108"><![CDATA[tating early disease detection and offer-             POST-MORTEM INTERVAL (PMI)
         ing customised therapeutic suggestions.

         AI-powered imaging  technologies  have                An investigator, when he comes across
         significantly elevated the field of radiol-           a cadaver, needs to determine the inter-
         ogy,  expediting,  and  refining  the  inter-         val between the time of death and the
         pretation of medical visuals like X-rays,             discovery  of  the  body.  PMI  signifies

         CT scans, and MRLs. Furthermore, AI                   the duration since death occurred. This
         accelerates drug discovery by analysing               PMI, coupled with forensic reports,
         molecular structure, thus propelling ad-              holds significance in legal proceedings,
         vancements  in  the  developmental  land-             influencing  the  court’s  decision  to  ac-

         scape.                                                cept or reject claims made by suspects
                                                               and witnesses. The process of assessing
         FORENSIC ODONTOLOGY                                   the time since death during forensic ex-
                                                               aminations relies on the application of

         A convolutional neural network (CNN)                  AI technology. This involves estimating
         is a type of deep learning model capable              markers in the blood, such as lactate de-
         of receiving an input image, assigning                hydrogenase (LDH) and aspartate ami-
         significance  to  various  features/objects           notransferase (AST) as protein indica-

         in the image, and distinguishing between              tors, and cholesterol as lipid indicators.
         them. Commonly utilised  AI technolo-                 Once the data is entered into the system,
         gies in this field consist of deep neural             it generates an accurate prediction about
         networks (mostly applied in age estima-               PMI.

         tion, sex determination, and conducting
         dental  comparisons),  artificial  neural             AI  IN  3D  CEPHALOMETRIC
         networks, ML, and computational tech-                 LANDMARK IDENTIFICATION
         niques. AI algorithms with sophisticated

         computations  were  developed  to  iden-              The examination of intricate cranial and
         tify individuals based on dental records              facial  formations  falls within the do-
         in mass disasters. Neural network-based               main of orthodontics. Historically, these
         algorithms are accessible to users with-              structures were crucial for accurate treat-

         out  extensive  expertise,  offering  preci-          ment  planning,  deleting  lines,  angles,
         sion while minimising human bias in the               and planes on craniofacial  structures,
         gender assessment of skeletal  remains.               particularly visible in lateral X-rays. An
         Neural networks  have the potential  to               automated 3D cephalometric algorithm

         significantly impact fields ranging from              with reliable precision identifying spe-
         archaeology to forensics.                             cific points consistently could serve as a
                                                               valuable tool. This tool isn’t designed to







                                                           99

                                                                             Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="109"><![CDATA[replace humans, but rather to address hu-              CONCLUSION
        man errors which are impossible to elimi-
        nate due to interobserver variability                  AI offers benefits to forensic medicine ex-

                                                               perts in autopsy and toxicological analy-
        TOXICOLOGY AND DRUG                                    sis. Global forensic experts must provide
        ANALYSIS                                               accurate data initially, including autopsy

                                                               findings,  images,  injury  patterns,  bio-
        Various contemporary techniques for tox-               marker stats, and algorithms. ML excels
        icological assessment exist. A few meth-               at data processing, identifying  complex
        ods encompass photometric  analysis,                   patterns, and consistent decision-making,
        chromatography, neutron activation anal-               but it has limitations like inflexibility and

        ysis, and  high-performance  liquid  chro-             is unsuitable for certain cases. AI enhanc-
        matography. Despite  the  advancements,                es forensic practice, but ethical and legal
        human errors persist. AI plays a pivotal               challenges must be addressed to its full
        role in mitigating this issue. By impart-              potential.

        ing a machine with a set of algorithms, it
        analyzes with enhanced precision. AI can               REFERENCES
        be  integrated  with  robotics  to  automate
        specific toxicological aspects to perform              1.  Gupta, R. (2023). Role of artificial in-

        computations to solve chemical equations                   telligence (AI) in forensic and medi-
        and theories, along with predicting reac-                  cal  sciences. IP International  Journal
        tion  products. It has also advanced  sta-                 of Forensic Medicine and Toxicolog-
        tistical methods for evaluating chemical                   ical  Sciences,  8(2), 47. https://doi.

        data and aiding in compound and spec-                      org/10.18231/j.ijfmts.2023.009
        trum analysis.                                         2.  Frankenfield, J. (2023). Artificial intel-
                                                                   ligence: What it is and how it is used.

                                                                   Investopedia.        https://www.investo-
                                                                   pedia.com/terms/a/artificial-intelli-
                                                                   gence-ai.asp













               Ms. Arsha Sahadevan                                        R Bhavitha Sri
                        21FASB55

                         Vth Sem





                                                          100


      Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="110"><![CDATA[DIGITAL STEGANOGRAPHY




        AS A THREAT










          INTRODUCTION                                        Digital steganography refers to the dis-
                                                              guising and transferring  of computer
          Digital steganography was coined at the             data so that the true nature of the data
          end of the 15th century. Steganography,             being transferred is hidden from all but

          the art of concealing messages or in-               the sender and receiver. In some cases, it
          formation within seemingly innocuous                could pose a security risk if used for ma-
          files, has transcended its historical role          licious purposes, but it’s not inherently a
          as a tool for covert communication and              threat on its own. Security measures and

          espionage. The purpose of steganogra-               vigilant  monitoring  can help mitigate
          phy is covert communication  to hide                potential  risks associated  with digital
          a message from a third party. Stegan-               steganography.
          ography hides the covert message but

          not the fact that two parties are com-              MOTIVE
          municating with each other. This hid-
          den technique enables the embedding                 There are a number of motivations for
          of data within images, audio files, vid-            criminals  and terrorists to use digital

          eos, and even seemingly harmless text,              steganography. Digital steganography
          creating a veil of secrecy that can be              can be used to hide internet communi-
          exploited by cybercriminals, state ac-              cations among conspirators as they plan
          tors, and malicious entities. This hid-             their  criminal  activities.  Also, insiders

          den avenue poses a unique and potent                who  have  access  to  financial  or  other
          threat as it allows for the clandestine             types of sensitive information in a com-
          exchange of information, from leaking               puter data system can use steganography
          sensitive  data  to facilitating  cyber-at-         to conceal the theft and unauthorised

          tacks, thereby challenging the conven-              transfer of the data to outside sources.
          tional paradigms of digital security and
          surveillance.                                       STEGANOGRAPHY AS A THREAT


          UNDERSTANDING  DIGITAL                              Steganography can be a threat because

          STEGANOGRAPY                                        it allows individuals to hide sensitive in-





                                                          101

                                                                              Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="111"><![CDATA[formation  within  seemingly  innocuous

         files, like images or audio files. This hid-             networks could  use steganography
         den information could include anything                   to communicate plans, coordinate at-
         from confidential documents to malicious                 tacks, or traffic illegal goods without
         code. Since it’s hard to detect, it can be               drawing attention from law enforce-

         used for covert communication, data ex-                  ment agencies.
         filtration, or even to deliver malware.
         undetected. This makes steganography a               4.  Blackmail  and Extortion:  Hidden
         potential tool for cybercriminals, terror-               messages could be used to threaten

         ists, or espionage activities. Hackers can               individuals or organisations with the
         hide data inside images using a technique                exposure of sensitive or embarrassing
         called least significant bit (LSB).                      information, which leads to potential
                                                                  blackmail or extortion scenarios.

         MANAGEMENT OF
         STEGANOGRAPHY AS A THREAT                            5.  Recruitment and radicalization:
                                                                  Extremist  groups might  use stegan-

         1.  Information Leakage: Malicious                       ography  to  distribute  propaganda,

             actors can hide sensitive information                recruit  new members,  and radical-
             such as trade secrets, military plans, or            ise individuals while evading online
             personal  data  within  harmless-look-               monitoring.
             ing files. This information can then be

             transmitted or leaked without raising            6.  Financial  Fraud:  Criminals  could
             suspicion,  potentially  causing  finan-             see steganography to embed instruc-
             cial, political, or personal harm.                   tions within images to manipulate fi-
                                                                  nancial systems, execute fraudulent

         2.  Insider Threats: Employees with ac-                  transactions,  or carry out phishing
             cess to sensitive information  might                 attacks.
             use steganography to leak company
             data, intellectual  property, or cus-            7.  Malware Distribution: Malware

             tomer information without detection.                 creators  can  embed  malicious  code
             It can cause data breaches, sensitive                within  images  or  other  files  using
             data leakage, production loss, and or-               steganography. When a user unknow-
             ganisational reputation damage.                      ingly opens or downloads these files,
                                                                  hidden malware  can be unleashed,

         3.  Terrorism and Organised Crime:                       leading  to data  breaches, system
             Terrorist organisations and criminal                 compromises, and even more.








                                                          102


      Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="112"><![CDATA[8.  Censorship circumvention: In re-                 harmless files. This technology can be
            gions with strict internet censorships,           exploited by cybercriminals,  hackers,
            steganography  can  be  employed  to              terrorists, and other malicious actors to

            transmit  restricted  content,  allowing          facilitate various illicit activities. From
            individuals to bypass government fil-             leaking  sensitive data and distributing
            ters and access information  or com-              malware to coordinating  cyberattacks
            municate freely.                                  and evading censorship, the covert na-
                                                              ture  of steganography  allows these

         9.  Cyber Espionage: State-sponsored                 threats to operate under the radar of con-
            or  criminal  groups might  use  steg-            ventional security measures.
            anography  to communicate  covertly,

            enabling  them to plan and execute                As  society becomes increasingly de-
            cyber-attacks, gather intelligence,  or           pendent  on digital  communication  and
            engage in espionage without being                 data exchange, it is crucial for individ-
            detected by traditional security mea-             uals, organisations, and governments to
            sures.                                            be aware of the potential risks posed by

                                                              steganography and to implement robust
         10.  Disinformation Campaigns: Hid-                  security measures to detect and counter-
            den messages could be used to spread              act its misuse.

            false or misleading information,in
            contributing  to disinformation  cam-             Though  steganography  is not  imple-
            paigns that manipulate  public  opin-             mented in wider ways, it can be used as
            ion, incite fear, or create confusion.            the best security tool. The main problem
                                                              in today’s world is securing their  data

         Overall, the covert nature of steganogra-            confidentially. The techniques used cur-
         phy makes it a versatile tool for evading            rently are not considered the best; this
         detection and carrying out a wide range              can only be replaced by steganography.

         of  malicious activities,  posing  serious
         threats to society’s security, privacy, and          REFERENCES
         stability
                                                              1.  Fiscutean, A. (2021, September 15).
         CONCLUSION                                               steganography  explained  and how

                                                                  to protect  against it . CSO. https://
         As a result, steganography presents a sig-               www.csoonline.com/article/571265/
         nificant threat to society due to its ability            steganography-explained-and-how-

         to conceal information within seemingly                  to-protect-against-it.html








                                                          103


                                                                                 Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="113"><![CDATA[2.  Kessler, G. C. (2004, July). overview of
               steganography for computer forensic
               examiner.  Office of Justice Programs.
               https://www.ojp.gov/ncjrs/virtual-  li-

               brary/abstracts/overview-steganogra-
               phy-computer-forensics-examiner


            3.  Wingate,  J. E. (2007, April).  digital

               steganography: threat or hype? Office
               of Justice Programs. https://www.ojp.
               gov/ncjrs/virtual-library/abstracts/
               digital-steganography-threat-or-hype




















                                                                    Mohana. S. G. S,

                                                               Nancy arul mary lucas,

                                                                    Shanoy angel. V,
                                                                         Divya. M
































                                                          104


      Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1]]></page><page Index="114"><![CDATA[CONTRIBUTORS






                   Students:

                       » Shreya Gupta - 21FRSB51

                       » Riya Ghosh - 22FRSB49

                       » Plathothathil Rachael - 22FRSB45
                       » Debashis Das - 22FRSB24

                       » Sasha Vassula Fernandes - 21FRSB48

                       » Pereppaden Ancila Robinson - 22FRSB44

                       » R Bhavitha Sri - 21FRSA39
                       » A Sherlin Gomez - 21FRSB01

                       » Bhavya Kamath - 21FRSB17

                       » Allen Jose Tomyachen - 22FRSB05

                       » Anashwara Pramod - 22FRSB08
                       » Pavithra Manoj - 21FRSA38

                       » Riya Reji - 21FRSA42

                       » Anna Roy - 21FRSA10

                       » Naveena Joy - 21FRSB36
                       » Mohana. S. G. S - 21FRSA29

                       » Nancy Arul Mary Lucas - 21FRSA33

                       » Shanoy angel. V - 21FRSA56

                       » Divya. M - 21FRSA19





























      Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1
                                                          105]]></page><page Index="115"><![CDATA[CONTRIBUTORS






                   Alumni 2020 Batch:

                       » Alfymol Anto Narithookkil

                       » Joshua Stephen

                       » Riya Thomas
                       » Nisarga Lakshmi

                       » C N Manu Shree

                       » Sreelakshmi N M

                       » Pooja V
                       » Disha S N



























































                                                                                    Veritas Volume :3, Issue :1
                                                          106]]></page><page Index="116"><![CDATA[]]></page></pages></Search>